<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>E.W. his Thameseidos Deuided into three bookes, or cantos.</title>
            <title>Thameseidos</title>
            <author>Wilkinson, Edw. (Edward), fl. 1600-1603.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1600</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15365</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25642</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111739</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847016</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847016</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12019</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15365)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12019)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 401:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>E.W. his Thameseidos Deuided into three bookes, or cantos.</title>
                  <title>Thameseidos</title>
                  <author>Wilkinson, Edw. (Edward), fl. 1600-1603.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. W[hite] for Simon Waterson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1600.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>E.W. = Edward Wilkinson.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁴.</note>
                  <note>Vertical chain lines.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12019:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12019:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>E. W.</hi> HIS THAMESEIDOS.</p>
            <p>Deuided into three Bookes, or Cantos.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nunquam stigias ibit ad vmbras Inclita virtus.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of William White (McKerrow no. 165): "a pelican in her piety, on a shield of irregular outline"</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed by <hi>W. W.</hi> for <hi>Simon Waterſon,</hi> 1600.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12019:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="1" type="book">
               <pb facs="tcp:12019:2"/>
               <head>THAMESEIDOS, <hi>Liber Primus.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>NOw gentle blaſtes, forerunners of the day,</l>
                  <l>Had ſummond hatefull Darknes packe away:</l>
                  <l>And Horror, Coachman vnto ougly night,</l>
                  <l>Made his blacke Steedes poaſt with all ſpeed he might,</l>
                  <l>From foorth our <hi>Hemiſphere,</hi> not daring bide</l>
                  <l>To looke vpon <hi>Aurorás</hi> gorgious pride.</l>
                  <l>And now from new ſowſ'd wife, the fierie Sunne</l>
                  <l>Was riſen, and from <hi>Ocean</hi> ſeas begunne,</l>
                  <l>To driue his golden Chariot, that he might</l>
                  <l>To all the world declare his glorious light.</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Thameſis,</hi> the faireſt Queene on earth,</l>
                  <l>To ſolemniſe her annuall day of birth,</l>
                  <l>Appareled in Robe of pureſt white,</l>
                  <l>All thicke of golden ſhimiring Spangles dight;</l>
                  <l>Which gainſt the Sunne reflecting beames did caſt,</l>
                  <l>As do the Starres, that in the heauens are plâſt.</l>
                  <l>Her haire bound vp in knots like golden Wier,</l>
                  <l>And crownd with Garlands of ſweete ſmelling Brier:</l>
                  <l>Vnto a Meddow by, his flowing ſtreames</l>
                  <l>Did goe: where ſhe from heat of <hi>Phoebus</hi> beames,</l>
                  <l>Vnder the coole ſhade of the ſpreading Trees,</l>
                  <l>Did meane to ſport and ſing ſweete virolees.</l>
                  <l>With her faire <hi>Nimphes,</hi> each hauing in her hand,</l>
                  <l>To fill with precious flowers a little maund.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It was about the ſelfe ſame time of yeare,</l>
                  <l>When from the midſt of heauen the Sunne doth beare</l>
                  <l>His ſcorching heate, and makes it ſwiftly role,</l>
                  <l>Vnto the Starres of the <hi>Antartique</hi> Pole.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:3"/>
                  <l> Then when <hi>Pomona</hi> lades her ſlender bowes,</l>
                  <l>To ſerue <hi>Autumnus</hi> her diſcaſed ſpowſe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Autumnus</hi> who in preſſe with naked feete,</l>
                  <l>From ſweete ripe Grapes, make pleaſant Wines to fleete.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In Inorie hand faire <hi>Thames</hi> a Maund did hold,</l>
                  <l>Moſt rarely painted, and adornd with gold:</l>
                  <l>Which precious Iewell great <hi>Ocean</hi> did</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Doris</hi> giue, what time he did her wed:</l>
                  <l>Which precious rich Maund louely <hi>Doris</hi> after,</l>
                  <l>Did giue to <hi>Thames</hi> her derling and her daughter.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Vpon that Maund were many Hiſtories</l>
                  <l>Depicted in ſuch rare and curious wiſe,</l>
                  <l>That ſeemd as Art with Nature ſtroue t'excell</l>
                  <l>In the rare workmanſhyp, for none could tell,</l>
                  <l>Saue <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulcane,</hi> who ſome ſayd, did make the ſame,</l>
                  <l>How like to it, an other Maund to frame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There might y'haue ſeene a very ſtately Bed,</l>
                  <l>Made like a Boat; which certaine <hi>Tritons</hi> did</l>
                  <l>With their ſtrong ſcalie backes vphold and ſtay,</l>
                  <l>All armde with Oares, all coullard like the Sea:</l>
                  <l>Bout whom, faire <hi>Sea-Nimphs</hi> ſported chearfully,</l>
                  <l>Delighted with the <hi>Tritons</hi> company:</l>
                  <l>Where, on the poop, ſtood <hi>Neptune;</hi> who did hold</l>
                  <l>In his right hand his Trident tinde with gold.</l>
                  <l>And vnder his left arme a winding Shell,</l>
                  <l>Like thoſe from whence (as ancient Poets tell)</l>
                  <l>The heades of <hi>Tiber</hi> and of <hi>Nilus</hi> ran,</l>
                  <l>Or ere their floodes vnto the ſalt Sea came.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ioues</hi> braine-bred-daughrer at the prow was placed,</l>
                  <l>Armed as then when ſhe from heauen chaced</l>
                  <l>The hundred handed <hi>Titan</hi> to his graue,</l>
                  <l>Vpon the Fiſh that did <hi>Orion</hi> ſaue.</l>
                  <l>The Teſterne like a Tile, all couered</l>
                  <l>With purple Veluet richly imbrodered,</l>
                  <l>With orient round Pearle was ſupported by;</l>
                  <l>Certaine faire <hi>Sea-Nimphes</hi> on whoſe head did lie,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:3"/>
                  <l> The Arched Ribbes in very ſtately order,</l>
                  <l>As on ſo many columnes: on a border</l>
                  <l>Bout which was painted the imagerie</l>
                  <l>Of many Sea-gods, very curiouſly;</l>
                  <l>With Curtaines ſutable thereto: whereon</l>
                  <l>The Romaine <hi>Lucrece</hi> liueleſſe, pale, and wan,</l>
                  <l>Lay all beſmeared in her owne goare blood,</l>
                  <l>Which with a Poyniard her owne hand had ſhod,</l>
                  <l>As ſacrifice vnto her chaſtitie;</l>
                  <l>Which was bereau'd by <hi>Tarquine</hi> ſpightfully.</l>
                  <l>And there by cunning Woorkman curiouſly,</l>
                  <l>Was made a Land-ſhaft, in which one might ſee,</l>
                  <l>Steepe craggie Rockes, high Mountaines, ſhady Woodes,</l>
                  <l>Greene pleaſing Fieldes, and crooked winding Floodes;</l>
                  <l>Where, in the middle of a pleaſant Lawne,</l>
                  <l>There was a ſtately Fountaine ſweetely drawne;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe water from a Harpies breaſt did fall,</l>
                  <l>Of Braſſe, into a Ceſterne paued all</l>
                  <l>With poliſht Marblé, and with Porphire ſtone;</l>
                  <l>In which the Painter had his cunning ſhowne,</l>
                  <l>In neately laying of his cullours, that</l>
                  <l>It ſeemd a true Fount, and no counterfect:</l>
                  <l>In which was chaſt <hi>Diana</hi> with her Nimphes,</l>
                  <l>All naked, bathing of their tender limbes;</l>
                  <l>On whom <hi>Acteon</hi> in the changed ſhape</l>
                  <l>Of fearefull Deare, full greedily did gape,</l>
                  <l>Turned thereto becauſe he ſhould not tell,</l>
                  <l>Had ſeene <hi>Diana</hi> naked in a Well:</l>
                  <l>By whom were made his wearie Hound that lapped</l>
                  <l>The water which from foorth the Fountaine drapped;</l>
                  <l>Whom fearing, he did ſeeke to flie: for as</l>
                  <l>His body, ſo his minde transformed was;</l>
                  <l>And on the hanger of a Hill hard by,</l>
                  <l>The Dogges pinching his hantches you might ſee;</l>
                  <l>A rewfull ſight, yet could not be amended,</l>
                  <l>Since he <hi>Dianas</hi> grace had ſo offended.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:4"/>
                  <l> And bout the Verges ſeemely to behold,</l>
                  <l>Trailes of <hi>Moriſco</hi> workes were wrought in gold.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus louely <hi>Iſis</hi> with his comely traine</l>
                  <l>Of beauteous <hi>Nimphes,</hi> into the Meddow came;</l>
                  <l>Where, on one ſide a ſhady Forreſt grew;</l>
                  <l>To which <hi>Aurora</hi> oft her ſelfe withdrew,</l>
                  <l>To heare her Loues complaint, and where the Moone,</l>
                  <l>Oft ſtayde to looke vpon the Latmian Lowne:</l>
                  <l>In which did grow the tough and hardie Aſhe,</l>
                  <l>The builder Oke; Holme fit for Carters laſh,</l>
                  <l>Chaſt louely <hi>Daphne</hi> cloſed vnder rinde,</l>
                  <l>Inceſtuous Mirh, that weepeth ſtill of kind:</l>
                  <l>Then peacefull Oliue, and the holſome Pine;</l>
                  <l>The ſayling Firre, and eke the drunken Vine:</l>
                  <l>Vpon whoſe boughes, pearcht the laſciuious Sparrow,</l>
                  <l>The temperate Turtle, and the wight wingd Swallow,</l>
                  <l>Who flying ſinges, and ſinging ſtudieth where,</l>
                  <l>With more art then with coſt, her neſt to reare:</l>
                  <l>The which, as patterne may be looked on</l>
                  <l>By rareſt Archytect and cunningſt man.</l>
                  <l>The little Owſle, and the mounting Larke;</l>
                  <l>The prettie Quaile, and charitable Storke,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe kindneſſe to olde Parents children learne;</l>
                  <l>For oft to aged Parents you are more ſterne.</l>
                  <l>High flying Cranes, by whoſe orderly flight,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mars</hi> firſt was taught in rancked ſquadrons fight.</l>
                  <l>And Peacoks, which againſt the Sunne do reare</l>
                  <l>Their painted tayles with <hi>Argus</hi> eyes made faire.</l>
                  <l>With little Nightingales, who diuerſly</l>
                  <l>With changed notes do make ſweete melodie,</l>
                  <l>Feigning ſometime a baſe, ſometime a trebble,</l>
                  <l>Often a meane, then ſweetely foorth do warble</l>
                  <l>A deſcant, which the mindes of ſtanders by,</l>
                  <l>Doth rauiſh, hearing ſuch ſweete harmonie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>On th'other ſide, a ſecret Caue was ſeene,</l>
                  <l>Which for his fitneſſe, often times hath beene</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:4"/>
                  <l> A refuge for thoſe <hi>Nimphes,</hi> the which would ſhunne,</l>
                  <l>The ſcortching heate of Midday of the Sunne:</l>
                  <l>The entrance deckt with Moſſe, pleaſing the ſight,</l>
                  <l>And alway freſh and greene for more delight,</l>
                  <l>To land-ward did there riſe a Hill ſo high,</l>
                  <l>That wel-nie it did face the azurd skie:</l>
                  <l>From foote of which, did runne a purling Brooke</l>
                  <l>Through the Meade, with many a winding crooke:</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſlyding ſtreames the heauens calme ſeemd blew,</l>
                  <l>Whence ſtore of pleaſure to the eye-ſight grew;</l>
                  <l>Yet clearer then was <hi>Aganippe</hi> Fount,</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Acidalia,</hi> where the <hi>Charicts</hi> wount</l>
                  <l>To bath their Iuorie breaſtes and golden haire,</l>
                  <l>Ere they make readie <hi>Cithereas</hi> care.</l>
                  <l>About whoſe bankes did grow ſmall tangled Trees,</l>
                  <l>Which made it ſeeme a heauen to gaſers eyes:</l>
                  <l>Whoſe boughes the needie Wood-man neare had cut,</l>
                  <l>Nor hungrie Beaſt the tender ſhootes had brut.</l>
                  <l>And in the middle of that Meddow grew</l>
                  <l>A ſtately Beech, which his large armes foorth threw</l>
                  <l>To ſhadow them that vnder her ſhould ſport,</l>
                  <l>To which with <hi>Lea, Iſis</hi> did reſort</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Lea;</hi> on whoſe bankes <hi>Ardea</hi> was turned</l>
                  <l>Into a Bitterne, cauſe ſhe <hi>Glaucus</hi> ſcorned.</l>
                  <l>Whilſt <hi>Colne,</hi> and <hi>Kenet,</hi> with the faire <hi>Chrew</hi> went</l>
                  <l>To gather Flowers of moſt pleaſing ſent;</l>
                  <l>For there were Roſes with Virmilion died,</l>
                  <l>Coole Daſies, and white Lillies; Summers pride:</l>
                  <l>The Marigold, that doth affect the Sunne,</l>
                  <l>Hiding her beautie when his light is gonne:</l>
                  <l>The Bee alluring Thime, the ſweete Coſtmarie,</l>
                  <l>Gray Lauender, and ſtrong ſenting Roſemarie,</l>
                  <l>And what elſe might be pleaſing to the view,</l>
                  <l>Within this faire and princely Meddow grew:</l>
                  <l>But that which garniſht moſt this Paradiſe,</l>
                  <l>Were <hi>Iſis</hi> louely looke, and ſparkling eyes.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l> For marke how brighter <hi>Cinthia</hi> doth appeare</l>
                  <l>Aboue the Starres within her motiue Spheere:</l>
                  <l>So much more fairer did this louely Dame</l>
                  <l>Exceede thoſe comely <hi>Nimphes,</hi> that which here came.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Not ſhee, whom <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus</hi> gaue for the rich Ball,</l>
                  <l>The cauſe of tenne yeares warre, and <hi>Troyes</hi> fall:</l>
                  <l>Nor that faire Dame whom <hi>Ioue</hi> in ſhape of Swan,</l>
                  <l>Whylome did court, when he her loue firſt wan:</l>
                  <l>Nor yet <hi>Europa,</hi> whoſe loue made him take</l>
                  <l>A proude Bulles ſhape (tho then when he did make)</l>
                  <l>To looke like a faire vntamed Heyfer:</l>
                  <l>Had he turnd to a Bull, it had been better;</l>
                  <l>For Beautie might in any poynt compare</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Iſis,</hi> tho they were exceeding faire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>You learned <hi>Muſes,</hi> race of mighty <hi>Ioue,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That often ſport within a ſacred Groue,</l>
                  <l>In pleaſant Tempe, and do dayly drinke,</l>
                  <l>Of thoſe cleare waues that flow from <hi>Pinples</hi> brinke.</l>
                  <l>O you that guide their enterpriſes right,</l>
                  <l>Who take in hand to graue with rareſt ſlight,</l>
                  <l>Vpon the Alter of Muemoſine,</l>
                  <l>Within the Temple of Immortalitie,</l>
                  <l>Sweete pleaſing beautie, which elſe ſubiect were,</l>
                  <l>In ſhade of laſting ſilence ſtill to ere,</l>
                  <l>Guide me, that with your helpe I may begin</l>
                  <l>To frame <hi>Thams</hi> beautie; whoſe like neare hath bin:</l>
                  <l>And graunt theſe Rithmes, which ſlenderly are done,</l>
                  <l>May ſhew hereafter when as I am gone.</l>
                  <l>She was the fairſt and moſt accompliſht Dame,</l>
                  <l>Excelling 'all whom Nature ere did frame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Her heauenly Head the miracle of Nature,</l>
                  <l>Surpasſing farre the faireſt earthly creature:</l>
                  <l>With yelow Tramels all of beaten gold,</l>
                  <l>VVhich gaſers thoughts in curled knots did hold;</l>
                  <l>Seemd ouerſpred with flowers freſh and gay,</l>
                  <l>The mirtle Foreſts where the loues do play.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:5"/>
                  <l> Like to a Table was her Front to ſee,</l>
                  <l>Of whiteſt Marble, ſeate of Maieſtie:</l>
                  <l>VVell poliſhed, as on a ſummers daie,</l>
                  <l>VVithouten waues vnited ſeemes the Sea:</l>
                  <l>VVhere <hi>Cupid</hi> had an Alter built to offer,</l>
                  <l>Their hartes that did refuſe his lawes to ſuffer.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Her Eye-lids blacke, of Heben arches made,</l>
                  <l>VVere like the bow that <hi>Pſiches</hi> husband had;</l>
                  <l>In which ſo liberall was Nature to her,</l>
                  <l>That euery one ſuſpected (that did view her)</l>
                  <l>She onely 'made faire <hi>Iſis</hi> to deceaue them:</l>
                  <l>And both of ſight and iudgement to bereaue them.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Of different force were her two ſparckling eyes,</l>
                  <l>Diſdaine in th'one, grace in the other lyes:</l>
                  <l>Two eyes? O no, rather two heauenly Starres;</l>
                  <l>Th'one proffering Peace, the other threatning Warres:</l>
                  <l>In which <hi>Mars</hi> baſtard Boy, his lodging tooke</l>
                  <l>Thence wounding them which at thoſe ſtarres did looke.</l>
                  <l>Her Noſe did ſeeme (being ſomewhat highly rayſed)</l>
                  <l>A little Hill betweene two Vallies placed.</l>
                  <l>Her round and tender Eare, white poliſhed:</l>
                  <l>VVith Rubies hung her Cheekes embelliſhed:</l>
                  <l>Cheekes which with liuely Cynab're ore ſpred.</l>
                  <l>Seemd like the Morning, new riſſe from her bed.</l>
                  <l>Not all thoſe Flowers ſprung from Princes gore,</l>
                  <l>Nor <hi>Amaranthus</hi> loues Flower made of Yore,</l>
                  <l>Like colour had to hers, which did amaze</l>
                  <l>Thoſe careleſſe eyes, that on her cheekes did gaze.</l>
                  <l>Full was her Mouth of thouſand Odours ſweete,</l>
                  <l>VVhere there in ſingle ranckes did ſeemely meete</l>
                  <l>Bright orientall Peatles in ſtead of Teeth:</l>
                  <l>All which, embalmd the Heauens with their breath.</l>
                  <l>From thence ſweete word and pleaſing ſmiles did come,</l>
                  <l>All made to charme, and make beholders dome:</l>
                  <l>And which hard Rockes that ſtand in Seas aloft,</l>
                  <l>Could by their mighty power, of hard make ſoft.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:6"/>
                  <l> Round was her Chin, with in whoſe dimples lay</l>
                  <l>Enchaunting ſpels, tho ſeeming faire and gay.</l>
                  <l>Her Neck a ſtay, this little worlde to'pholde,</l>
                  <l>Of Iuorie was, or Alabaſter mould,</l>
                  <l>Plaſt on two hils in whitnes that did paſſe.</l>
                  <l>Her ſnow-white Breaſts that was <hi>Agenous</hi> laſſe:</l>
                  <l>Betweene which hils, Loue often times did lurke,</l>
                  <l>When cruell ſtratagems he meant to worke.</l>
                  <l>Her little, but long fingered Hand, more white</l>
                  <l>Then whiteſt Lillies that the Spring doth dight:</l>
                  <l>With enterchanged Vaines adorned was.</l>
                  <l>Her ſmall Feete ſuch as ſome ſay <hi>Tethis</hi> has:</l>
                  <l>With which ſhe nimbly could trip ore the Lawns,</l>
                  <l>And chace ſwift Row-bucks, and young wanton Fawns.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But for thoſe parts the which her Garments hid,</l>
                  <l>What ſhould we ſay? Surely dame Nature did</l>
                  <l>Keepe thoſe thinges ſecret, leaſt they ſhould excell</l>
                  <l>All ſhe had made in heauen, in earth, in hell.</l>
                  <l>But O! what boots it to haue thinges ſurpaſſe,</l>
                  <l>Since faireſt thinges do fade like Sommers graſſe:</l>
                  <l>Alas nought in this worlde doth firmely ſtay,</l>
                  <l>But turneth ſtill like Billowes of the Sea:</l>
                  <l>VVhich neare do ceaſe to roule till with great rore,</l>
                  <l>Their ruſhing beat and breake againſt the ſhore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And thou the cauſe of this vnſtableneſſe,</l>
                  <l>That doſt delight in nought but fickleneſſe;</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe cuſtomes neuer to abide in one,</l>
                  <l>But vſeth headlong dayly throw vs downe,</l>
                  <l>VVhen we are rayſ'd by thy benignitie,</l>
                  <l>Vnto the top of all felicitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>While thus with their faire <hi>Nimphs</hi> this louely Queene</l>
                  <l>VVas in this pleaſant Meade, by them was ſeene</l>
                  <l>A Sheapheard, in the pride of all his dayes:</l>
                  <l>VVho whilſt his tender Flocke on ſalts did graſe,</l>
                  <l>Sate ſenceleſſe, like an Image made of ſtone</l>
                  <l>Long while, at laſt fetching a deepe ſad grone</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:6"/>
                  <l> Of inward griefe, the treweſt ſigne of all;</l>
                  <l>They foorth his eyen perceiud ſalt teares to fall:</l>
                  <l>So after great <hi>Ioues</hi> hidious thunders paſt,</l>
                  <l>A cloude of raine, the heauens doth ouercaſt:</l>
                  <l>And when his teares were ſpent, with heauie cheare,</l>
                  <l>Sang to his Pipe this Song; which they did heare:</l>
                  <l>And hearing, could not chooſe but ſimpathiſe</l>
                  <l>His heauie griefe with water in their eyes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O whither (quoth he) whither ſhall I flie,</l>
                  <l>To purchaſe ende vnto my miſerie?</l>
                  <l>VVithin what Rocke, or to what deſart place,</l>
                  <l>That neuer is enricht by <hi>Phaebus</hi> face?</l>
                  <l>Shall I vnfold in great and greeuous paine,</l>
                  <l>Which makes me wretcheder then any Swaine?</l>
                  <l>If there be any place where dayly cries</l>
                  <l>The Night-rau'n and the Owle, that by night flies,</l>
                  <l>Whereto no liuing wight doth ere reſort:</l>
                  <l>From whence foule Winter neuer doth depart,</l>
                  <l>And where the Spring her verdure will not ſowe,</l>
                  <l>A place of deadly horror and foule woe,</l>
                  <l>Where ougly ſorrow dayly may preſent,</l>
                  <l>Her ſelfe before mine eyes me to torment:</l>
                  <l>That will I chooſe as beſt befitting mee,</l>
                  <l>In this diſtreſſe and great extremitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And you my little flocke, the ſmall remaine</l>
                  <l>Of a farre greater, which once more my payne</l>
                  <l>Might with moſt neighbour flockes haue made compare</l>
                  <l>For number or for wooll, both fine and faire:</l>
                  <l>Then when for change of paſture ſillie I,</l>
                  <l>In th'Aprill of mine age left <hi>Germanie;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where I mongſt Stadian bowers had nigh been ſlaine,</l>
                  <l>Cauſe I my Princeſſe honour did maintaine:</l>
                  <l>Which was, and is, more dearer vnto mee,</l>
                  <l>Then is the precious apple of mine eie:</l>
                  <l>And hoping for I wat not what to gaine,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Englands</hi> pleaſant ſoyle brought you againe.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:7"/>
                  <l> Goe wander, goe; and take your libertie,</l>
                  <l>Graſing where is beſt paſture, while that I</l>
                  <l>Bewaile m'<hi>Icarian</hi> flight in mounting pride,</l>
                  <l>Plumed with waxe-forg'd-wings, which thought to ride</l>
                  <l>Aboue the cloudy welkin of the ayre,</l>
                  <l>To view the order their <hi>Latonas</hi> heire;</l>
                  <l>Holdeth in guiding of that glorious light,</l>
                  <l>That is the nouriſh of each liuing wight;</l>
                  <l>But was deceaud for comming neare the Sunne:</l>
                  <l>My winges did melt, and I did tumble downe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O had I kept along the humble gill,</l>
                  <l>When firſt I did attempt to climbe the hill.</l>
                  <l>Or had I bounded mine ambitious minde,</l>
                  <l>Which careleſſe thought to builde aboue the winde,</l>
                  <l>Sprung from remembraunce of thoſe deedes were done</l>
                  <l>By my great Graundſirs, long-ſince dead and gone:</l>
                  <l>And a deſire to regiſter my'name,</l>
                  <l>Mought them within the ſacred booke of fame:</l>
                  <l>Then might I now as I haue done before,</l>
                  <l>Paſture you ſtill along this pleaſant ſhore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Or had not rather greete <hi>Chruſophilus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whoſe greedy humor pasſing couetous,</l>
                  <l>Thought all that went beſide himſelfe quite loſt:</l>
                  <l>Mee too much wronged, and mee too much croſt;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſoule with many filthy crimes made blacke,</l>
                  <l>Now fleetes about <hi>Auernus</hi> fearefull lake:</l>
                  <l>Then might I now as I haue done before,</l>
                  <l>Paſture you ſtill along this pleaſant ſhore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For which, you Lordes of the infernall Bower,</l>
                  <l>Who ore deceaſſed ſoules haue mighty powet,</l>
                  <l>T'inflict, or to remit their puniſhment:</l>
                  <l>O doe you all at my requeſt aſſent,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ixion</hi> from his wheele a while to take;</l>
                  <l>And falſe <hi>Chruſophilus</hi> faſt there to make.</l>
                  <l>Or if great <hi>Iunos</hi> wrath be not yet done,</l>
                  <l>Let <hi>Siſiphus</hi> t'hen leaue his rowling ſtone.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:7"/>
                  <l> Or pull from <hi>Cawcaſus Prometheus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And let the <hi>Vulturs</hi> teare <hi>Chruſophilus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or if that may not be, <hi>Ioue</hi> angrie yet,</l>
                  <l>O then drag <hi>Tantalus</hi> foorth of his pit.</l>
                  <l>And let <hi>Chruſophilus</hi> vp to the chin,</l>
                  <l>Still, but in vaine, wade vp an'downe therein.</l>
                  <l>Let him at that faire ſeeming fruite, oft ſnatch;</l>
                  <l>Which thereby hanges, but neuer any catch.</l>
                  <l>A torment well beefitting ſuch a wight,</l>
                  <l>Who liuing ore his owne, had neuer might;</l>
                  <l>And let his late made gentle of spring, which</l>
                  <l>Are with ſtolne Plumes of others pride made rich:</l>
                  <l>Diſpoyld thereof like to their Grandſirs fare,</l>
                  <l>Who vnto <hi>Ceres</hi> ſlauiſh ſeruants weare.</l>
                  <l>And for aſſenting to my wiſhed boone,</l>
                  <l>Sad <hi>Hecatombes</hi> by mee ſhall be done,</l>
                  <l>And monthly I will offer a blacke Ramme,</l>
                  <l>As ſigne that I am thankfull for the ſame,</l>
                  <l>For had not he lately from mee bereft</l>
                  <l>Vniuſtly all my Sheepe, ſaue theſe few left;</l>
                  <l>To ſtanch his neuer ſatisfied luſt</l>
                  <l>Of Golde, earths droſſe, that doth conſume with ruſt;</l>
                  <l>Then might I now, as I hane done before,</l>
                  <l>Paſture you ſtill alongſt this pleaſant ſhore.</l>
                  <l>But ſince it cannot be as twas of late,</l>
                  <l>Since Fortune now hath giuen me the mate,</l>
                  <l>Diſpoyld me quite of all my woonted mirth,</l>
                  <l>Clad me with woes, and throwne me to the earth:</l>
                  <l>And like a Tyrant triumphes ouer me,</l>
                  <l>That fore her proſtrate on the ground doth lie;</l>
                  <l>Neare reckning whether it be iuſt and ſound,</l>
                  <l>To trouble him, lies groueling on the ground.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O you the remnant of a greater flocke,</l>
                  <l>Goe get you gone, while to ſome deſart rocke</l>
                  <l>I make repaire, where for my bed ſhall be</l>
                  <l>The cold dry ground, whereon I ſtill will lie;</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:8"/>
                  <l> For morning mattens, mournings full of care:</l>
                  <l>For walkes, the wretched pathes of foule diſpaire:</l>
                  <l>For meate, ſad diſcontent: for drinke, ſalt teares:</l>
                  <l>For nightly ſleepes, nought elſe but ſlumbring feares;</l>
                  <l>Till thoſe laſt dueties I doe pay to Nature,</l>
                  <l>Which I am bound too, beeing a mortall creature:</l>
                  <l>What time my ſoule freed from this earthly gaile,</l>
                  <l>Where now it tyred lyes, ſhall to thee vaile:</l>
                  <l>Of faire <hi>Eliſium</hi> fly, where voyde of paine,</l>
                  <l>Mongſt bleſſed ſoules in ioy it ſhall remaine.</l>
                  <l>And thou ſweete Pipe, the which wonts oft diſplay</l>
                  <l>My wronges vnto theſe Woodes, theſe Rockes, and Sea,</l>
                  <l>And moouedſt them at once to rew my lot,</l>
                  <l>When lyuing men ſeemd ſenceleſſe, and would not;</l>
                  <l>But helde hard hartes, the which I do repent,</l>
                  <l>More harder farre, then hardeſt Adamant.</l>
                  <l>From that rude race, degenerating nought,</l>
                  <l>Which was of hard Stone, by <hi>Deiecalion</hi> wrought.</l>
                  <l>Here hang thou (therewith on a Beechen tree</l>
                  <l>He hung his Pipe) for now no more for thee,</l>
                  <l>Nor for thy ſugred melodie I care,</l>
                  <l>(Quoth he) which done like one drownd in diſpaire:</l>
                  <l>Thence heauie he departed, pasſing nought,</l>
                  <l>What Fortune, or foule Enuie could alot.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>On whom, whilſt <hi>ISIS</hi> lookt, perceiue ſhe might</l>
                  <l>The Sea to ſwell, which did her much affright:</l>
                  <l>For ſhe diſcerned on their toppes to ride</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Neptune,</hi> poaſting to the ſhore with ſpeede.</l>
                  <l>Whoſe comming ſo amaſ'd the fearefull <hi>Thams,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Who knew full well that he thoſe ſcorching flames,</l>
                  <l>VVith her faire eyes within his breaſt had wrought,</l>
                  <l>VVould ſeeke to quench by farce, if he her caught)</l>
                  <l>As in a ſhadie Wood the hydeous ſtroke</l>
                  <l>Of ratling Thunder on the ſodaine broke,</l>
                  <l>Doth ſcare the ſmall Birdes, pearched on the ſpray:</l>
                  <l>And like how Fowle that by a Riuer play,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:8"/>
                  <l> Spying a Falcon towring in the skie,</l>
                  <l>Straight leaue their ſport, and for their ſafetie flie,</l>
                  <l>VVithouten order crying here and there:</l>
                  <l>So <hi>ISIS</hi> and her <hi>Nimphes,</hi> being in feare</l>
                  <l>Of hated <hi>Neptune,</hi> from thence ſtraight gan fly,</l>
                  <l>Shreeking and crying very pitteouſly.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Aye me, What is this world but vanitie?</l>
                  <l>Subiect to change; full of vnconſtancie:</l>
                  <l>Now is the Welkin glorious to the eie,</l>
                  <l>Clad in a Mantle of an aſurd die.</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Phaebus</hi> now his faire light doth diſplay,</l>
                  <l>When by and by a blacke Cloud foorth the Sea</l>
                  <l>Doth riſe and darke the heauens were <hi>Iouiall,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Troubling both ayre and earth with waters fall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Aye, now I ſee that mourning followes mirth,</l>
                  <l>That ſorrow driueth pleaſure from the earth;</l>
                  <l>That happineſſe doth not long time remaine,</l>
                  <l>But ere it is at full begi'nes to waine:</l>
                  <l>That all in vaine man ſtriues to keepe his ſtate,</l>
                  <l>When dangerous ſtormes labour it to abate:</l>
                  <l>That vainely men doe boaſt of Fortunes fauours,</l>
                  <l>Since like a weather-cocke ſhee alwayes wauers,</l>
                  <l>Threatning them moſt, and bringing ſooneſt vnder</l>
                  <l>Thoſe, at whoſe fortunes moſt the world did wonder.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And ſtrange, what ere within this world is done,</l>
                  <l>Ordayned was before this world begun:</l>
                  <l>So that great IOVE, who moderateth Heau'n</l>
                  <l>As ſoueraigne, and commaunds ore Gods and men:</l>
                  <l>At whoſe becke, earth and ayre, and all elſe moue,</l>
                  <l>Will not o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> enterpriſe the Fates to proue:</l>
                  <l>Whom neither prayers, nor ought elſe can reſiſt,</l>
                  <l>Cauſe ſtill th'are fixt, and ſtill in one perſiſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS Lib. Prim.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="book">
               <pb facs="tcp:12019:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>THAMESEIDOS, <hi>Liber Secundus.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHen cold ſtaru'n Winter white with Ice and Snow</l>
                  <l>Declining from our Hemiſphere doth goe:</l>
                  <l>And watrie Planets plunged deepe do yeelde,</l>
                  <l>Their mantions vnto <hi>Hyems</hi> pleaſant childe.</l>
                  <l>When luckleſſe Eccho learnes againe to ſing,</l>
                  <l>The paſtorall Songes which Sheapheard neare a Spring;</l>
                  <l>Or hard beſide ſome murmering Brooke repeat,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt little Lambkins bout the fieldes do bleat.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The amorous God that louely <hi>Tyro</hi> knew,</l>
                  <l>In likeneſſe of her Husband <hi>Enipeu,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hated by Grecian <hi>Nimphes,</hi> him whilome loued,</l>
                  <l>And by the <hi>Thuſcane, French,</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh</hi> glouted:</l>
                  <l>Remembring the rare beautie that was ſaide</l>
                  <l>T'adorne faire <hi>ISIS</hi> face, himſelfe araide:</l>
                  <l>And falling foorth the ſtraights of <hi>Gibraltare,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where by <hi>Alcides</hi> plaſt to <hi>Coloms</hi> are,</l>
                  <l>His nimble teame of <hi>Dolphins</hi> he made poſt,</l>
                  <l>Along the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> and the <hi>Gallicke</hi> coaſt:</l>
                  <l>And when he came where <hi>Englands</hi> pride doth pay</l>
                  <l>Her dayly tribute to her Soueraigne Sea,</l>
                  <l>There he at laſt vnyoakt his wearie teeme,</l>
                  <l>And went to ſeeke the faire commended Queene:</l>
                  <l>Whom by her ſiluer ſlyding ſtreames he found,</l>
                  <l>Amid her Maydens on th'enameld ground:</l>
                  <l>Whoſe face faire without art, did quickly daze</l>
                  <l>His eyes, that greedely on it did gaze,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Phaebus</hi> doth our <add>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ver</add> feeble ſight,</l>
                  <l>When we dare looke <del>on</del> 
                     <add>upon</add> his daſeling light;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:9"/>
                  <l>For like the man that vnawares doth ſee</l>
                  <l>A blaſing Comet in the ſable skie,</l>
                  <l>Not hauing ere before ſeene ſuch a ſight,</l>
                  <l>Aſtond, long ſtares vpon the ſtreaming light:</l>
                  <l>This great God long beheld her beauteous face;</l>
                  <l>Her beauteous face that Natures workes doth grace,</l>
                  <l>Till therewith rauiſht, he perceiud his hart</l>
                  <l>Began to faint, and wonted courage part:</l>
                  <l>And felt each ſenſe enchaunted by her beautie,</l>
                  <l>Forget his wonted office, and his duetie:</l>
                  <l>Which wanton <hi>Cupid</hi> ſaw as he did lie</l>
                  <l>Lurking vnder a ſandie banke, to prie</l>
                  <l>On <hi>JSIS</hi> beautie, and being v'ery glad,</l>
                  <l>That then the long deſired meane he had</l>
                  <l>T'auenge him for the enuious tale he tolde,</l>
                  <l>Vnto his mother then, when faine he would</l>
                  <l>Haue maried <hi>Pſiches:</hi> ſtraight he to the hart</l>
                  <l>Strake <hi>ISIS</hi> with a leaden headed dart:</l>
                  <l>Then with an other all of burniſht gold,</l>
                  <l>He warmd his hart, that had long time been cold;</l>
                  <l>And made him ſupplyant, craue remedie</l>
                  <l>For thoſe hot flames that in his breſt gan frie:</l>
                  <l>But craue in vaine; for when his ſuite ſhe heard,</l>
                  <l>At firſt ſhe waxed pale, being afeard:</l>
                  <l>But after, like the Roſe in month of May,</l>
                  <l>Coullard with heate of <hi>Phaebus</hi> goulden ray</l>
                  <l>For ſhame her face did ſeeme, and to him ſayd,</l>
                  <l>That ſhe long ſince had vowd to die a Mayde:</l>
                  <l>Therefore in vaine he labourd, and in vaine</l>
                  <l>Should ſue, if in the end he hop't to gaine</l>
                  <l>That guerdon, whereto they haue onely right,</l>
                  <l>Who vnder Loues laſciuious banner fight:</l>
                  <l>And therewith with her faire troope went her way,</l>
                  <l>Leauing the God behind, who did not ſtay</l>
                  <l>Long after her; but wroth that ſhe was gon,</l>
                  <l>He ſtudied long which way ſhe might be won</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:10"/>
                  <l> Vnto his will; like to a gallant Souldier,</l>
                  <l>Who for the firſt repulſe doth not giue ouer</l>
                  <l>The fortreſſe, which to gaine he goes about:</l>
                  <l>Who thereby more enrag'd, doth waxe more ſtoute;</l>
                  <l>And backe returnes, meaning in ſpight of foes,</l>
                  <l>To ſacke the walles, and enter ere he goes.</l>
                  <l>But after he had long time beate his braine,</l>
                  <l>And could deuiſe no way how her to gaine,</l>
                  <l>He vowd the next time that he could come to her,</l>
                  <l>To vſe his force, and not his words to woe her.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Within a Wood from <hi>ISIS</hi> ſtreames a part,</l>
                  <l>There is a Caue made in deſpight of art,</l>
                  <l>So fitly is the growing Marble wrought,</l>
                  <l>To beautifie the entry of the Vault:</l>
                  <l>Through this a Riuer glides, whoſe ſandes do show,</l>
                  <l>Like thoſe that do in weſterne <hi>Tagus</hi> grow:</l>
                  <l>Which left the earth ſome while, her ſelfe to drowne,</l>
                  <l>Within this darke, but pleaſant manſion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Much like the <hi>Nubian Niger,</hi> which doth ſlide</l>
                  <l>In one place vnder earth of no man ſpide:</l>
                  <l>Hither proud <hi>Medwaie,</hi> one of <hi>JSIS</hi> traine,</l>
                  <l>In hunting hauing loſt his company came;</l>
                  <l>Where, with her dayes toyle ouer-wearied,</l>
                  <l>Downe on a bancke ſhe layde her weary head,</l>
                  <l>Meaning when ſhe had ſlept a while, to go</l>
                  <l>After her loſt Companions: but ô,</l>
                  <l>We entend often one thing, when an other</l>
                  <l>Croſſeth our purpoſes; the which, ô there</l>
                  <l>Was to be ſeene: for that place which ſhe thought</l>
                  <l>Should worke her reſt, her moſt diſquiet wrought:</l>
                  <l>Becauſe a <hi>Satire</hi> that before had ſpide her,</l>
                  <l>Taking the Vault when ſhe thought none had eyed her,</l>
                  <l>Who did imagine ſhe was <hi>Phaebus</hi> ſiſter:</l>
                  <l>And with <hi>Endimion,</hi> who had often kiſt her,</l>
                  <l>Appoynted there to meete, whereby they might</l>
                  <l>Reape that ſame harueſt, that doth Loue delight,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:10"/>
                  <l> Did follow her: and had't been true, he then,</l>
                  <l>Meant to bewray it vnto Gods and men:</l>
                  <l>All in reuenge of that diſgrace was done,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Marſius,</hi> by the God that guides the Sunne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But when the fearefull <hi>Satire</hi> came vnto</l>
                  <l>The entraunce of the Caue, he durſt not go</l>
                  <l>Boldly in to't, afrayde leaſt he eſpied,</l>
                  <l>His baſe leawd enterpriſe might be denied:</l>
                  <l>But villain-like ſtale ſoftly to, and peeped</l>
                  <l>At firſt there in, where he a <hi>Nimph</hi> that ſleeped</l>
                  <l>On the bare floare did ſee, whom ſtraight he knew:</l>
                  <l>But nor for <hi>Phaebe,</hi> nor one of her crew.</l>
                  <l>And woondring at his hap, forgate anon</l>
                  <l>The Goddeſſe, and her deare <hi>Endimion:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And looke how that ſame <hi>Faun</hi> that doated on</l>
                  <l>Faire <hi>Iole,</hi> ſtoode like a ſenſeleſſe ſtone,</l>
                  <l>Scard and amaſ'd, when ſoftly he had crept,</l>
                  <l>It being darke where as <hi>Alcides</hi> ſlept,</l>
                  <l>Thinking that he faire <hi>Iole</hi> had bin,</l>
                  <l>Cauſe ſhe was armd with Club and Lions skin.</l>
                  <l>So ſtood this <hi>Satire</hi> for a while aſtond,</l>
                  <l>Viewing the ſleeping <hi>Nimph</hi> on the bare ground:</l>
                  <l>Yet that vnlookt-for change pleaſd him ſo well,</l>
                  <l>That ſtraight to toying on her lippes he fell,</l>
                  <l>Whereby he cauſd her from her ſleepe awake;</l>
                  <l>Where ſhe ſpying this <hi>Satire,</hi> ſtraight gan quake,</l>
                  <l>And ſtood euen like, if that the like might bee:</l>
                  <l>Scard and amaſed at his companie,</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Gadian Spaniards,</hi> when as they did ſee,</l>
                  <l>The valiant <hi>Engliſh</hi> by their chiualrie,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Caeſarean</hi> conquerours of their towne before,</l>
                  <l>They are ſuſpected they had gaind their ſhore.</l>
                  <l>Or like to him whoſe fellowes ſodainlie,</l>
                  <l>Stroke with a Dart ſent from <hi>Joues</hi> armorie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But as the Birde beſnarled in the net,</l>
                  <l>Which the falſe Fowler cloſely for her ſet,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:11"/>
                  <l> Altho faſt bound, yet flutters with her winges,</l>
                  <l>And to be gone, ſtandes byting of the ſtringes:</l>
                  <l>So did ſhe with her tender force withſtand,</l>
                  <l>And ſtrugled ſtrongly both with foote and hand,</l>
                  <l>Thinking her ſelfe thereby againe to free</l>
                  <l>Away out of his brutiſh companie;</l>
                  <l>And with ſharpe wordes reuilde him, to maintaine</l>
                  <l>Her honour ſpotleſſe, but twas all in vaine:</l>
                  <l>For the young <hi>Satire</hi> fealt ſhe was vnable,</l>
                  <l>Beeing ſo tender bônd, with him to graplet</l>
                  <l>Yet ſeeing her ſo hot, and out of quiet,</l>
                  <l>And very deſirous for to put her by it,</l>
                  <l>So gently as he could he askt her why,</l>
                  <l>She ſo ſhould ha:e the harmeleſſe <hi>Satirie?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who anſwered ſtraight, Their foule deformed ſhapes,</l>
                  <l>Their manners rude, vnfit for Maydens laps;</l>
                  <l>Did make her loath their vile baſe companie:</l>
                  <l>To which the <hi>Satire</hi> foorthwith did replie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sweete <hi>Nimph</hi> (quoth he) What? is it theſe that grow</l>
                  <l>Foorth of our forheads, that diſlike you ſo?</l>
                  <l>(Poynting vnto his little hornes) If theſe?</l>
                  <l>That God which conquerd <hi>Jndia,</hi> and did pleaſe</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Candian Queene,</hi> had ſuch: or if too red</l>
                  <l>My face doth ſeeme? know <hi>Phaebus</hi> from the bed</l>
                  <l>Of his faire Loue aryſing, redder farre</l>
                  <l>Doth looke; yet rode he oft in <hi>Climens</hi> Carre.</l>
                  <l>But happily, nor theſe our Hornes nor Face,</l>
                  <l>But theſe our hayrie Breaſtes, worke our diſgrace:</l>
                  <l>Which I confeſſe are rough, but like his Breaſt</l>
                  <l>Where louely <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus</hi> oft hath ſtolne her reſt.</l>
                  <l>Nor ſhould we ought the more ill ſhapen ſeeme,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe Goate-like wee clouen footed beene,</l>
                  <l>Since <hi>Cupids</hi> mother is wed vnto him,</l>
                  <l>That hath a pool-foote, and halts of a lim.</l>
                  <l>And well I wot, wee <hi>Joue</hi> our ſhape did take</l>
                  <l>When to <hi>Antiope</hi> he loue did make:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:11"/>
                  <l> Therefore I muſt conclude, if Nature had</l>
                  <l>This perfect ſhape of ours imperfect made,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe in heauen and earth the like there are,</l>
                  <l>Mongſt God and men to be excuſ'd it were:</l>
                  <l>This ſayd, he threw her downe vpon the ſand,</l>
                  <l>For, O her force too weake was to withſtand:</l>
                  <l>And there in ſpight of her, he puld the flower,</l>
                  <l>The fragrant Roſe, which neare before that hower;</l>
                  <l>(Tho ofted ſought) by any was obtayned:</l>
                  <l>Hard was her hap that ſo vile ſlaue it gained.</l>
                  <l>That done, he ſhooke her off, as great men now,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe that their turnes haue ſerued vſe to do;</l>
                  <l>And thence departed, leauing her full woe,</l>
                  <l>And ſorrowfull behind, for ſhe did know,</l>
                  <l>She like the Roſe, was cropt from natiue ſtem,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe vertues wholy loſt, do nor younge men,</l>
                  <l>Nor louely Maydes delight, or ought content</l>
                  <l>Either for ſhew, or for their pleaſing ſent.</l>
                  <l>Yet went ſhe home againe, but did not tell,</l>
                  <l>What hard misfortune was to her befell,</l>
                  <l>But proudly, as before, when ſhe was free,</l>
                  <l>Shee preſſeth next her Miſtris ſtill to bee,</l>
                  <l>And iets it by her ſide; ſhe neuer ſhowde</l>
                  <l>By any action ſhe awry had trode.</l>
                  <l>Nor did her fellowes ere her fault perceiue:</l>
                  <l>So ſtudied ſhe their eye ſight to deceiue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet after this, ſcarce <hi>Phaebe</hi> the ninth time</l>
                  <l>Had ſhowne her ſelfe to this our northerne Clime,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Iſis</hi> almoſt fainting thorow heate,</l>
                  <l>And hunting in the chace, being in a ſweate:</l>
                  <l>By chaunce a faire and pleaſant Lawne eſpyed,</l>
                  <l>Through midſt of which a ſhallow Brooke did ſlide:</l>
                  <l>And liking well the place, the vpper brimme,</l>
                  <l>Toucht with her foote, and finding coole and trimme</l>
                  <l>The water, willed all her Maydens there,</l>
                  <l>To bath themſelues, which when <hi>Medwaie</hi> did heare,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:12"/>
                  <l> She hung the head, afraid ſhe ſhould bewray,</l>
                  <l>That yet none knew, and onely ſought delay,</l>
                  <l>Till iealous <hi>Thams</hi> whether ſhe would or no,</l>
                  <l>Cauſed her Maydes her garments to vndo;</l>
                  <l>Where, with her naked body ſtraight was ſhowne,</l>
                  <l>Her ſhame; the which vnwilling to haue knowne,</l>
                  <l>She couerd with her hands: but all ſerud nought,</l>
                  <l>Twas knowne, and ſhe confeſt where it was wrought:</l>
                  <l>Deſiring pardon, cauſe twas forced on her,</l>
                  <l>And gainſt her will, ſhe ſuffred that diſhonour.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But as <hi>Diana</hi> raged when ſhe knew</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Calisto,</hi> one of her faire retinew</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Ioue</hi> was forced; ſo did <hi>ISIS</hi> now:</l>
                  <l>And ſtraight commaunded her from thence to goe,</l>
                  <l>And tolde her for her leawd fact angered,</l>
                  <l>That whether to the Northerne Pole ſhe fled,</l>
                  <l>Where windie <hi>Boreas</hi> doth dayly ſtrow</l>
                  <l>The tops of <hi>Hyperborean</hi> hilles with Snow:</l>
                  <l>Or to the <hi>Tropicks,</hi> where <hi>Apollos</hi> torch</l>
                  <l>With extreame heate the ſandy ground doth ſcortch:</l>
                  <l>Yet therefore ſhould ſhe not eſcape or flie</l>
                  <l>The iuſt reward of her hypociſie,</l>
                  <l>Which could ſo vilde a fact ſo long time hide,</l>
                  <l>From being by her, or her fellowes ſpide.</l>
                  <l>Which when poore <hi>Medwaie</hi> heard, diſcomfited;</l>
                  <l>Vnwitting what to doe; for feare halfe dead:</l>
                  <l>From thence ſhe traueld by vncertaine wayes,</l>
                  <l>Like a great Shippe in the wide Ocean Seas;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſtately Maſte being ſpent, and proud Sayles loſt,</l>
                  <l>Is by each waue hither and thither toſt:</l>
                  <l>And ſtill bewailde her miſerable ſtate,</l>
                  <l>Her wretched life brought to ſo low a rate:</l>
                  <l>Life ſeeming long to folke in miſerie,</l>
                  <l>But ſhort to thoſe liue in felicitie.</l>
                  <l>Yet comfortleſſe as ſhe was, like that wight,</l>
                  <l>Which on the high <hi>Alpes,</hi> hauing loſt by night</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:12"/>
                  <l> His way, and knoweth not which hand to turne,</l>
                  <l>Sits on a Bancke, where while as he doth mourne</l>
                  <l>His happes vnto the ſable mantled Skies,</l>
                  <l>Farre off ſome Sheapheards by a fier eſpies,</l>
                  <l>She farde; hearing the iangling of a Bell:</l>
                  <l>Following the which, ſhe came vnto a Cell,</l>
                  <l>Amidd the ſhadow of faire ſpreading trees:</l>
                  <l>Through which did breath a coole refreſhing brees,</l>
                  <l>Where the woods Burgeſes did dayly ſing</l>
                  <l>Sweete Laies vnto a pleaſant purling Spring,</l>
                  <l>That thereby ranne: which pleaſing melodie</l>
                  <l>Might well delight, with his rare harmonie</l>
                  <l>Each mortall creature; whereas ſhe did ſee</l>
                  <l>An olde Man clad in ruſſet, on his knee,</l>
                  <l>Deuoutly mumbling Mattens: which good ſight,</l>
                  <l>At that time cheard her ouer dulled ſpright:</l>
                  <l>And till his mourning dueties he had ended,</l>
                  <l>At th'entrance of the Cell ſhe him attended:</l>
                  <l>Which finiſht, in ſhe went; whom when he ſpied,</l>
                  <l>What wight ſhe was much muſ'd, and more her eied.</l>
                  <l>All in a ſtoond, for ſillie man he nere</l>
                  <l>Before that time, like ſtrange ſight had ſeene there.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If ſhe ſome Goddeſſe were, he wiſt not well;</l>
                  <l>For of ſtrange Goddeſſes he had heard tell,</l>
                  <l>That would leaue hautie heauen, and reſort</l>
                  <l>To earthly Springes and Groues, to take their ſport.</l>
                  <l>Or if ſome <hi>Nimph</hi> to neighbour-woods belonging,</l>
                  <l>He did not know; yet for he had a longing</l>
                  <l>To wit what miſter wight ſhe was, he did,</l>
                  <l>After he thither had her welcome bid,</l>
                  <l>Intreate her shew, by knowing, which quoth he,</l>
                  <l>You may be duely honoured by me?</l>
                  <l>To which, <hi>Medwaie</hi> reuiud by's courteſie,</l>
                  <l>Him mildly anſwered: Father take not me</l>
                  <l>For other then a wretched wight, oppreſt</l>
                  <l>With mightie griefe, who craue but roome to reſt,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l> Till wearie limbes I haue refreſht againe,</l>
                  <l>Wherewith from foorth her eyes great ſhewers of raine</l>
                  <l>Fell downe her blubbred cheekes, whereat th'old man</l>
                  <l>Rewing her ſad diſtreſſed ſtate, began</l>
                  <l>Entreat her tell the cauſes of her griefe.</l>
                  <l>Who (ſighing) did her fortunes tell in briefe,</l>
                  <l>Both how the <hi>Satire</hi> in the Caue had vſ'd her,</l>
                  <l>And how therefore her Miſtris had refuſ'd her:</l>
                  <l>Which when the olde man heard, rewing her paine:</l>
                  <l>Alas faire daughter (quoth he) do not plaine,</l>
                  <l>For plaintes in theſe extreames do nothing vaile:</l>
                  <l>And tis not good in vaine to weepe and waile.</l>
                  <l>What woman, know there is no maladie</l>
                  <l>So hard to cure, but hath his remedie.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ioue</hi> doth not alwayes foorth his thunder caſt,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſtill doth the hot raging Sommer laſt,</l>
                  <l>Still <hi>Boreas</hi> doth not with impetuous ſway,</l>
                  <l>Raiſe mighty tempeſtes in the Ocean Sea.</l>
                  <l>Nor will theſe ſorrowes dayly on thee tende,</l>
                  <l>Thy patience prowd away from thee they'll wende.</l>
                  <l>All humaine accidents about do wheele,</l>
                  <l>And in one place do neuer ſoiorne ſtill,</l>
                  <l>No more then this great heau'n which dayly wee,</l>
                  <l>To turne with an vnwearie courſe do ſee:</l>
                  <l>Then euen as Heauen the which is Fortunes <del>horſe</del>
                     <add>ſourſe</add>,</l>
                  <l>About the earth doth keepe a laſting courſe:</l>
                  <l>So muſt we thinke thoſe fortunes which do fall,</l>
                  <l>Bred by high heauen; yet not perpetuall.</l>
                  <l>Cold Winter paſt, the healthy Spring doth come,</l>
                  <l>Then cholericke Sommer, after ſicke <hi>Autum:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor doth the influence of the heauens each hower,</l>
                  <l>Downe in one place ſtill good or bad lucke power:</l>
                  <l>Therefore ſad <hi>Nimph,</hi> ſince what is thee befall,</l>
                  <l>Thou canſt by no art backe againe recall.</l>
                  <l>Comfort thy ſelfe, and hope that God will ſend</l>
                  <l>To theſe thy griefe, when he ſees time, an end.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:13"/>
                  <l> In the meane ſeaſon, and till thou haue reard</l>
                  <l>Th'vnwildie burthen, and thy ſelfe haſt cheard,</l>
                  <l>Stay heere with me. So downe he wild her ſit,</l>
                  <l>And eaſe her wearie limbes: who glad of it,</l>
                  <l>Did reſt her ſelfe ſtraight on the duſtie ground,</l>
                  <l>As glad ſo good an harbour ſhe had found</l>
                  <l>In her great neede; as weather beaten Thruſh,</l>
                  <l>In a great ſhower is of a ſheltring buſh.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Not farre from hence where this old man abode,</l>
                  <l>Downe in a bottome grew a ſhadie Wood:</l>
                  <l>By which a Riuer ſerpenteth ſo cleere,</l>
                  <l>That from the bottome each thing doth appeare</l>
                  <l>Moſt liuely to the curious gaſers ſight:</l>
                  <l>Hither at any time no Shepheard might</l>
                  <l>Driue his rich fleecie bleating flocke to graſe,</l>
                  <l>For reuerence of thoſe <hi>Nimphes</hi> that haunt the place.</l>
                  <l>So't fortun'd as ſad <hi>Medwaie</hi> walkt about</l>
                  <l>One day to eaſe her griefe, ſhe did finde out</l>
                  <l>This pleaſant place, where by the Riuer ſide,</l>
                  <l>An entraunce through a ſtonie Rocke ſhe ſpide:</l>
                  <l>To which ſhe went, and did by ſteps deſcend,</l>
                  <l>Into a dark ſome Hall, through which ſhe wend:</l>
                  <l>Vnto a fayre roome, lightened all by arte,</l>
                  <l>For vnder ground it was, and farre apart</l>
                  <l>From ſight of heauen; the things that there made light,</l>
                  <l>Were precious Carbuncles, and Diamonds bright,</l>
                  <l>Reflecting Chriſtalls, Rubies cherrie red;</l>
                  <l>Rich Emeraulds, and Opols diſcoloured:</l>
                  <l>About which roome, the antique Images</l>
                  <l>Were plaſt, of many worthy perſonages.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fame</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Merline</hi> while he liu'd, did make</l>
                  <l>(Doating vpon a Lady of the lake)</l>
                  <l>This bowre, by his great ſkill at her requeſt,</l>
                  <l>And therin plaſt the pictures of the beſt,</l>
                  <l>And nobleſt wights that ſhould in <hi>Brittaine</hi> be,</l>
                  <l>After his death: There ſad <hi>Medwaie</hi> did ſee,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:14"/>
                  <l> On one ſide, the laſt man bore name of King,</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Brutes</hi> long raigning race, who thought to bring</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Armorick</hi> an Hoſt of valiant men,</l>
                  <l>To foyle the <hi>Saxons,</hi> that had footing then</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Brittaine</hi> tane, had not him Viſions ſtayde,</l>
                  <l>That wild to <hi>Rome</hi> his Iorney ſhould be made.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There was that <hi>Rhodericke,</hi> the great ſurnamde,</l>
                  <l>Who for deuiding <hi>Wales,</hi> was highly famde:</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Howel Dha,</hi> who auncient lawes corrected,</l>
                  <l>And Officers to ſee right done, elected:</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Griffeth Conon,</hi> who victorious raigned</l>
                  <l>Full fiftie yeeres; and when he peace had gayned</l>
                  <l>Vnto his Countrey, dyed: And <hi>Llewelline,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The braue laſt Prince of auncient <hi>Brittiſh</hi> line;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe life by them whom he did truſt, betrayde;</l>
                  <l>Alterd the gouernment which they had ſwayde</l>
                  <l>Two thouſand and foure hundred yeeres and od.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Aye me, that nought on earth hath his abode,</l>
                  <l>Heere permanent: aye me, that one mans fall,</l>
                  <l>Should be the ruine and decay of all</l>
                  <l>His houſe: aye me, I ſhould haue cauſe to rew</l>
                  <l>His loſſe, whoſe memorie olde griefes renew.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>On th' other ſide, in liuely Tables were</l>
                  <l>Pictures of Noble-men, and Ladyes faire:</l>
                  <l>Among all which, thoſe ſeemd the liuelieſt,</l>
                  <l>That ſhould liue vnder Faire <hi>ELIZA'S</hi> reſt:</l>
                  <l>Who though a Woman, yet beyonde compare</l>
                  <l>Of all the Princes in the world that are:</l>
                  <l>For in her raigne <hi>Arachne</hi> buſely,</l>
                  <l>Maketh her webs in ruſty Armorie:</l>
                  <l>And mightie Staues by rotten Woormes are eaten,</l>
                  <l>For want of vſe, that death had wont to threaten.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Theſe when ſhe had oreſeene, ſhe further went,</l>
                  <l>And to an other Roome thereby had ment</l>
                  <l>To goe, wherein the carued Pictures were,</l>
                  <l>Of thoſe that <hi>Englands</hi> royall Crowne ſhould weare:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l> And reached at the Key that thereby hung,</l>
                  <l>But could not moou't, ſo to the wall it clung:</l>
                  <l>For that ſame entraunce, cauſe ſhe was no Mayde,</l>
                  <l>(Like the faire Empreſſe who the Scepter ſwayde)</l>
                  <l>Was her denied, for ſo by hidden skill</l>
                  <l>Of Magicks art, and by infernall ſpell</l>
                  <l>Twas framde, that none might haue acceſſe therein,</l>
                  <l>That were defiled with Venerian ſinne:</l>
                  <l>Onely ſhe hapt through the Key-hole to ſpie</l>
                  <l>The faireſt Picture that ſhe ere did ſee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The counterfeict of Englandes Soueraigne,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>ELIZABETH,</hi> thrice happy in her raigne:</l>
                  <l>Vnder whoſe rule her Subiectes not deſier</l>
                  <l>To change their ſtate of womaniſh Empire:</l>
                  <l>Who whilſt hatefull <hi>Erinnis</hi> hell doth leaue,</l>
                  <l>And both with fier and ſword her neighbours greeue,</l>
                  <l>And in the murmure of a cruell ſtorme,</l>
                  <l>Which threates the machine of the world to harme:</l>
                  <l>In peace and quiet doth her Realme maintaine;</l>
                  <l>Suppreſſing Will, and ſuffering Iuſtice raigne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou moſt bright Sunne of this our Northern clime,</l>
                  <l>Liue thou for euer, or liue <hi>Neſtors</hi> time,</l>
                  <l>To maintaine Artes, as hitherto th'aſt done;</l>
                  <l>For wayle the <hi>Muſes</hi> muſt when thou art gone:</l>
                  <l>And if it fortune that at any time,</l>
                  <l>(Luckely) this ragged and vnpoliſht Rithme,</l>
                  <l>Into thoſe faire hands fall, that holdes the bridle,</l>
                  <l>With which thou iuſtly ruleſt many people;</l>
                  <l>Behold it with a fauourable eie,</l>
                  <l>And thinke that none can praiſe thee worthelie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>After the <hi>Nimph</hi> perceiude ſhe was denied</l>
                  <l>The entraunce of that roome, ſhe would abide</l>
                  <l>No longer there, but left the enchaunted place;</l>
                  <l>And thought returne, and ſhew what ſhe that ſpace</l>
                  <l>Had ſeene, vnto her Hoaſt: but being wearie</l>
                  <l>Of that vnweeldie burthen ſhe did carrie,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:15"/>
                  <l> She ſate her downe to reſt, and by and by,</l>
                  <l>Was faine for helpe vnto <hi>Lucina</hi> cry:</l>
                  <l>Who hearing her, ſtraite came, and with her goes</l>
                  <l>Some other <hi>Nimphes,</hi> to helpe her in her throwes:</l>
                  <l>Where they to get her, ſpeaking words of eaſe,</l>
                  <l>Did from her wombe a little babe releaſe.</l>
                  <l>Which by and by they laide in mothers lap,</l>
                  <l>Who with ſalt teares gan thus to waile her hap.</l>
                  <l>O cruell Miſtris (quoth ſhe) that exilde me,</l>
                  <l>When a rude <hi>Satire</hi> gainſt my will beguilde me.</l>
                  <l>Making me wander like a vacabone,</l>
                  <l>Through darke woods and ore bleere hills vnknowne:</l>
                  <l>Or like a Ghoſt, whoſe freinds forgotten haue,</l>
                  <l>The ſenceleſſe corps to burie in a graue.</l>
                  <l>Well hoped I for my long ſeruice don,</l>
                  <l>A better guerdon then this, to haue won:</l>
                  <l>But hopte in vayne; for woe! my curſed fate</l>
                  <l>I now do finde: but finde it all too late.</l>
                  <l>Who ſerueth thankleſſe folke, ſhal be rewarded</l>
                  <l>Not as they hopte, nor as they haue deſerued.</l>
                  <l>More had ſhe ſaide, had ſhe not bin by him</l>
                  <l>Euen then ſurpriz'd, that long to <hi>Thams</hi> had bin</l>
                  <l>A wearie ſuter, who then from his Sonne</l>
                  <l>Old <hi>Proteas,</hi> the ſkilfull God, did come.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Deepe in the <hi>Ocean,</hi> where yet neuer ground,</l>
                  <l>By longeſt fadome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                        <desc>•••…</desc>
                     </gap>e could ere be found:</l>
                  <l>Vnder a hollow Rocke, ther is a vault,</l>
                  <l>By often beating of great Billowes wrought:</l>
                  <l>So that it ſeemes to be the noble acte,</l>
                  <l>Of ſome rare Maſon, or skild Architect:</l>
                  <l>About which ſecret Caue, do daiy lorke</l>
                  <l>Amid the Rocks, the monſtrous cruell <hi>Orke:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The admirable <hi>Whale,</hi> which with great rore,</l>
                  <l>An other Sea, into the Sea doth poure:</l>
                  <l>All with the dead-ſleepe charming cold <hi>Torpil,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That knowes he carries in his flancke, that wil</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:15"/>
                  <l> Decaue the traitrous Fiſher of his pray:</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Scolopenders,</hi> who into the Sea</l>
                  <l>(Caught with ſharpe hooks) their entrails foorth do caſt:</l>
                  <l>And when the hookes are found, and daunger paſt,</l>
                  <l>Receiue them in againe; where as each one</l>
                  <l>His office holdes, as he before had done.</l>
                  <l>There dwels old <hi>Proteus,</hi> who by his great skill,</l>
                  <l>In the deepe ſecrets of blacke Magicke, will</l>
                  <l>Commaund <hi>Apollo</hi> ſtaie his foaming horſe,</l>
                  <l>Pluck downe heauens ſtars, &amp; ſtop faire <hi>Cinthias</hi> courſe:</l>
                  <l>And can great <hi>Pluto</hi> in his Realme affright,</l>
                  <l>When ere him liſt, to ſhew his powrefull might.</l>
                  <l>Heere had old <hi>Neptune</hi> bin, in hope to gaine</l>
                  <l>Some helpe from him, but then his arte prou'd vaine:</l>
                  <l>His Circles, Characters, ſtraunge words, all vſde</l>
                  <l>In order, number, time, his will refuſde:</l>
                  <l>For ſure that arte hath no power ore the ſoule,</l>
                  <l>Nor doth the world afoard an hearbe ſo foule:</l>
                  <l>Or potion made of poyſoned <hi>Minerall,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That can the minde vnwilling, make loues thrall:</l>
                  <l>Which made <hi>Ioues</hi> Brother diſcontent, thence part,</l>
                  <l>Diſpayring ere to eaſe his greiuous ſmart.</l>
                  <l>Since then, his hopes did faile, but as he went,</l>
                  <l>He heard a woman wofully lament,</l>
                  <l>With pitteous plaintes her greeuous martyrdome:</l>
                  <l>And going that way whence the plaintes did come,</l>
                  <l>Diſtreſſed <hi>Medwaie,</hi> he did hap to ſpie,</l>
                  <l>Bewayling of her Babies myſerie.</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſight did comfort him that hoped by her,</l>
                  <l>He might worke meanes to ſlake his tortring fier:</l>
                  <l>Which to effect and bring about the ſooner,</l>
                  <l>Knowing her fortunes, thus he ſtraight gan wooe her.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The much griefe (quoth he) I haue boren long,</l>
                  <l>Makes me the more to rue thy too much wrong,</l>
                  <l>Sad <hi>Nimph,</hi> all vndeſerude (I wot) by thee:</l>
                  <l>Wherefore if thou'lt, deuiſe, and but tell me</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:16"/>
                  <l> How I may quench theſe fiers in my breſt,</l>
                  <l>By fraude or force I paſſe not, I proteſt,</l>
                  <l>Of all thoſe many Sea-gods waite on mee,</l>
                  <l>The choiſe and comlieſt Ile beſto we on thee,</l>
                  <l>To be thy Huſband, in thy Miſtris place.</l>
                  <l>This ſaid, ſtraight <hi>Medwaie</hi> gan to waigh her caſe,</l>
                  <l>And ſadly counts the wronges ſhe had endured,</l>
                  <l>The great diſgraces nere to be recured:</l>
                  <l>All by her Miſtris, all without deſart,</l>
                  <l>As ſhe did iudge: yet iudg'd ſhe not her part,</l>
                  <l>Traytrouſly ſell her to her greateſt foe,</l>
                  <l>Though by her ſh'ad bin wronged farre much more:</l>
                  <l>But, but a ſmall while that thought did poſſeſſe her,</l>
                  <l>So much did <hi>Neptunes</hi> promiſ'd husband preſſe her,</l>
                  <l>'T ſhould ſeeme ſh'ad not forgot the ſport was made</l>
                  <l>Late in the Caue, how ere at laſt ſhe ſayde:</l>
                  <l>If to that place great God where ſometime you,</l>
                  <l>With all the Sea-gods of your retinue,</l>
                  <l>Were by <hi>Ocean</hi> richly entertained,</l>
                  <l>When he proud <hi>Thetis</hi> to his firſt wife gained:</l>
                  <l>Do goe to morrow ere the fierie Sunne</l>
                  <l>The harneſſe from his horſes hath vndunne:</l>
                  <l>There you that cruell Lady ſtraight ſhall finde,</l>
                  <l>That to vs both hath prooued too vnkinde:</l>
                  <l>Where hauing caught her, you may force her ſtench</l>
                  <l>Your bleeding woundes, and burning fiers quench.</l>
                  <l>But be you ſure to catch her by ſome ſleight,</l>
                  <l>Elſe will ſhe ſcape you (for ſhe's woondrous wight)</l>
                  <l>And ſerue you as <hi>Coronis</hi> hath to fore,</l>
                  <l>When ſhe out ran you on <hi>Phocaion</hi> ſhore:</l>
                  <l>But poore ſoule ſhee, no ſooner tolde this tale,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Neptune</hi> being afeard the time would faile,</l>
                  <l>If he would longer ſtay, in haſt did hie</l>
                  <l>To ſeeke his loue; which when <hi>Medwaie</hi> did ſee,</l>
                  <l>Repenting (but too late) that euer he,</l>
                  <l>Had her deceaued by his flatterie;</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:16"/>
                  <l> Euen as a wilde Bull darted by ſome one,</l>
                  <l>Begins to roare, and vp and downe to runne</l>
                  <l>Amid the preſſe, all feareleſſe of his harme:</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Medwaie</hi> vext, cauſe he did not performe</l>
                  <l>His oath; and for her fault in conſcience ſtunge,</l>
                  <l>Voyde of all patience, furilike flunge,</l>
                  <l>And oft for ſpight, her body threw to ground,</l>
                  <l>And all for ſpight her body to confound;</l>
                  <l>Till at the laſt, ſhe with her ſelfe did take</l>
                  <l>A truce, and ſummoned ſad wordes, to make</l>
                  <l>Her ſorrowes knowne; with which the quiet skie</l>
                  <l>She vext, and ſighing, thus at laſt gan crie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O fooliſh, that I was fooliſh and madd,</l>
                  <l>To thinke that falſe forſworen <hi>Neptune</hi> had</l>
                  <l>Fayth in his wordes, or to imagine hee,</l>
                  <l>(Changing his nature) would be true to mee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>You hollow Caues, grim <hi>Plutoes</hi> auncient place,</l>
                  <l>You helliſh furies, blacke nightes ougly race:</l>
                  <l>Thou triple headed <hi>Cerberus;</hi> and you</l>
                  <l>Infernall Floodes, O plundge mee deepe into</l>
                  <l>The bottome of that hot <hi>abiſme,</hi> where lie</l>
                  <l>Tormented Ghoſtes in wretched miſerie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O thou the guyder of the golden light,</l>
                  <l>O thou faire Queene that cleerely ſhinſt by night,</l>
                  <l>And you bright Starres that wander in the Skies,</l>
                  <l>If you haue power ouer our Deſtenies,</l>
                  <l>And that you be both of our good and ill,</l>
                  <l>The onely authours, then togither will</l>
                  <l>So many miſchiefes on my head to light,</l>
                  <l>As can, or may, vpon a wretched wight.</l>
                  <l>And thus as ſhe lamented in deſpaire,</l>
                  <l>Her tatterd Garments ſhee in peeces taire:</l>
                  <l>And her two ſnow-white handes plaighted together,</l>
                  <l>Enrag'd ſhe wrong, and thumped without meaſure<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Her tender Armes againſt the ſenſeleſſe ground,</l>
                  <l>And her ſmall Babe (ſtrange tale) being vnbound,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:17"/>
                  <l> And layde along vpon the ſoft greene gras;</l>
                  <l>No ſooner toucht the earth, but ſtraight wayes was</l>
                  <l>Ore-growne with earth; and from her tooes out went</l>
                  <l>Small writhing rootes in vnquoth wonderment.</l>
                  <l>And her ſmall body being leſſoned,</l>
                  <l>Into a ſmall long ſtalke was faſhioned.</l>
                  <l>To Flagges her fingers changd: and laſt of all,</l>
                  <l>Her Head turnd to that plant we Cats-talle call.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Which wondrous change, when <hi>Medwaie</hi> ſaw, ſhe mournd,</l>
                  <l>Cauſe to ſo vile a plant the Gods had turnd</l>
                  <l>Her guiltleſſe Babie; till at laſt euen ſhe</l>
                  <l>Did like to ſnow, that on the <hi>Alps</hi> doth lie</l>
                  <l>All Winter time; which when as weſterne windes,</l>
                  <l>Together with the warmth of Sunne vnbindes,</l>
                  <l>The clodded lumpes to water ſtraight doth change,</l>
                  <l>Making ſmall Brookes, as downe hill it doth range:</l>
                  <l>For ſhe conſuming vnto watrie teares,</l>
                  <l>Was to a Riuet turnde; the which now beares</l>
                  <l>Th'vnfortunate <hi>Nimphes</hi> name, fall'n by the fault,</l>
                  <l>Which in the Gaue was by the <hi>Satire</hi> wrought.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis Lib. Secund.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="book">
               <pb facs="tcp:12019:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>THAMESEIDOS, <hi>Liber Tertius.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IN all the world ſo great an enemie,</l>
                  <l>Either to man, or mans felicitie</l>
                  <l>There neuer was, if we do iudge aright,</l>
                  <l>And be not led away with blinded ſight,</l>
                  <l>Then is our owne ore-bold <del>ſeueritie:</del>
                     <add>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </add>
                  </l>
                  <l>For ſtill thereby fit oportunitie,</l>
                  <l>Our foes haue for to ceaze on vs, before</l>
                  <l>We thinke that they are neare aboard the ſhore:</l>
                  <l>Witneſſe faire <hi>Thames,</hi> who doubting nought at all,</l>
                  <l>Was nigh ſurpriſd, and made God <hi>Neptuns</hi> thrall:</l>
                  <l>Who next day, when <hi>Hiperions</hi> ſonne began</l>
                  <l>To driue his Chariot to the Ocean,</l>
                  <l>Ariued in the Meddow where as ſhe</l>
                  <l>Was ſporting in her Maydens companie:</l>
                  <l>Whom happilie faire <hi>Thamiſis</hi> eſpied;</l>
                  <l>And ſpying, her faire louely cheekes (ſtraight) died</l>
                  <l>With a Vermilion bluſh, abaſhed as</l>
                  <l>Naked <hi>Diana</hi> mongſt her Maydens was:</l>
                  <l>Then when ſhe in the cleere <hi>Gargaphian</hi> Spring,</l>
                  <l>By th'haples Nephew of the <hi>Thebane</hi> King</l>
                  <l>Vnwares was found; and from the place ſtraight fled,</l>
                  <l>Leauing her Maydes behind all in the Mead:</l>
                  <l>A way ſhe ran, as raging ſtormes doth flie,</l>
                  <l>Tumbling vp cloudes within the fable skie,</l>
                  <l>Nere looking backe, nor making any ſtaie:</l>
                  <l>So feared ſhe the ſoueraigne of the Sea.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Not halfe ſo faſt diſtreſſed <hi>Florimel</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Fled from the ſight of that <hi>Hiena</hi> fell,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:18"/>
                  <l> Which the diſpightfull Witch after her ſent,</l>
                  <l>To bring her backe, and her in peeces rent.</l>
                  <l>Nor halfe ſo faſt from <hi>Phaebus Daphne</hi> fled,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>ISIS</hi> now, to ſaue her maydenhead:</l>
                  <l>Whereat the Lord of the vnconſtant Sea</l>
                  <l>Did chafe, yet loth that ſhe ſhould get away,</l>
                  <l>He gan with ſugred ſpeaches for to woe her,</l>
                  <l>But all was ſpent in vaine, that he ſayd to her.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou that my ſoule holdes captiue in thine eyes,</l>
                  <l>(Quoth he) and ſtill new tormentes doſt deuiſe</l>
                  <l>To plague me, ſtay; and thoſe hot fiers fee,</l>
                  <l>That burning in my breaſt, haue vexed mee</l>
                  <l>Ere ſince the ſhaftes which from thy ſparkling ſtarres</l>
                  <l>Did come<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and wounded me all vnawares:</l>
                  <l>And in thy golden haire my hart was tane,</l>
                  <l>Which now diſpaires t'haue freedome ere againe:</l>
                  <l>But booteleſſe were theſe Wordes; which ſeeing, hee</l>
                  <l>A loude vnto her, thus againe gan crie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Stay cruell <hi>ISIS,</hi> harder farre then Flint,</l>
                  <l>And rougher then the Oake on <hi>Ida,</hi> ſtint</l>
                  <l>Thy haſtie pace; and cauſe the <hi>Nimphos</hi> thou doſt</l>
                  <l>Excell in fairenes, do not therefore boſt;</l>
                  <l>But thinke, that as thy flood beares to my realme,</l>
                  <l>with an infatigable courſe his ſtreame,</l>
                  <l>Returning nere againe vnto his head:</l>
                  <l>So th'howre the day, the day thy youth will lead,</l>
                  <l>Till on it death, or wrinckled age will ſeaſe:</l>
                  <l>Which come, thou'lt rue the time which thou didſt leaſe.</l>
                  <l>Loue therefore while as time is offerd thee,</l>
                  <l>And while thou mayſt againe like loued bee:</l>
                  <l>For times do change and alter euery day,</l>
                  <l>And in thoſe times we change, and doe decay:</l>
                  <l>Then preſent time's better, then time to come,</l>
                  <l>Since Golden, Siluer, Braſen age, is done;</l>
                  <l>And nought is left, but Irons cankred ruſt,</l>
                  <l>Which dayly turneth all from worſe to worſt.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:18"/>
                  <l> Looke but vpon the faire ſweete ſenting Roſe,</l>
                  <l>Which cropped from the tree whereon he growes,</l>
                  <l>Straight loſeth all the faireneſſe that it had:</l>
                  <l>And know, thy beautie one day, ſo will fade.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nor thinke thou canſt the Gods in heauen excell,</l>
                  <l>Since thundring <hi>loue,</hi> loues fier could not quell.</l>
                  <l>Since bright <hi>Apollo</hi> ſpite of all his art,</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Cupids</hi> ſhafts, was wounded to the heart:</l>
                  <l>Since the faire <hi>Ciprian</hi> Queene, wanton Loues Mother,</l>
                  <l>By no means could her youngling fier ſmother:</l>
                  <l>And that <hi>Diana</hi> on <hi>Endimion</hi> doated,</l>
                  <l>Yet for a maide, and chaſt, is ſtill reputed.</l>
                  <l>But rather thinke, though now from loue th'art free,</l>
                  <l>That loue will one day ſhew his power on thee.</l>
                  <l>Thou knoweſt, how late diſdainefull <hi>Ardea,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who <hi>Glaucus</hi> ſcornde; a God, and of the Sea:</l>
                  <l>Had her due merits on thy maidens ſtrond.</l>
                  <l>Be warn'd by her, that God which can commund<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>The greateſt Gods, will take reuenge on thee,</l>
                  <l>If thus thou doſt perſiſt in crueltee:</l>
                  <l>And if thou knowſt me not, then ſtay and view</l>
                  <l>What one he is, that for thy loue doth ſue.</l>
                  <l>I am not one that hauntes the craggie Rocks,</l>
                  <l>Yet Lord of Seas: nor tend I fleecie flocks,</l>
                  <l>From whom thou fleeſt, I thinke thou doſt not know;</l>
                  <l>For if thou didſt, thou wouldſt not vſe me ſo.</l>
                  <l>Were I a Saluadge, that mans fleſh doth eate,</l>
                  <l>A foule blacke <hi>Moore,</hi> a <hi>Tartar,</hi> or a <hi>Gete:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Had I bin foſterd in <hi>Hircanian</hi> wood,</l>
                  <l>By wilde <hi>Beares</hi> milke, or cruell <hi>Tygers</hi> blood:</l>
                  <l>Then mightſt thou ſcorne me iuſtly, and hold mee</l>
                  <l>Too too preſumptuous, thus to follow thee:</l>
                  <l>Then mightſt thou haue excuſe, and not be blam'd,</l>
                  <l>To let me die, with beauties fire inſlam'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But I in Seas keepe Court, my Temples ſtand.</l>
                  <l>At <hi>Istmus,</hi> and within <hi>Calabria</hi> land.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:19"/>
                  <l> In <hi>Italie</hi> the people do me honour,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Ioue</hi> himſelfe is knowne to be my brother.</l>
                  <l>With crooked Keele men learned firſt by mee,</l>
                  <l>To cut the Seas; and tame the Horſe was free.</l>
                  <l>And though my Beard ſeeme white, my Carkas olde,</l>
                  <l>Prooue mee, and thou ſhalt finde mee hot and colde:</l>
                  <l>Prooue mee, my artires wants no ſtrength: and though</l>
                  <l>That I ſeeme light, yet haue I pith enough.</l>
                  <l>Still pleaſure ſhall yeelde force vnto my raines:</l>
                  <l>Prooue, I will not deceiue thee of thy paines,</l>
                  <l>For oft vnidelie I haue ſpent the night,</l>
                  <l>And when I roſe, I haue bin freſh and light:</l>
                  <l>O runne no further then, but ſtay and proue,</l>
                  <l>Stay, and let's mutually ioy others loue.</l>
                  <l>Faine more he would haue ſpoke, but ſhe afrayd,</l>
                  <l>Fled faſt away, not heeding what he ſayd:</l>
                  <l>And as ſhe ranne, ſo meeting windes did blow,</l>
                  <l>That naked skinne aboue her knee did ſhow,</l>
                  <l>And her gold haire now fallen looſe and ſlacke,</l>
                  <l>At euery ſtep did waue behinde her backe:</l>
                  <l>All which, farre more did ſet his hart a fier,</l>
                  <l>And farre more did encreaſe his hot deſier,</l>
                  <l>So that he luſtely did mende his pace,</l>
                  <l>Hopeing to catch her, whom he had in chace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But as a Pirate hath bin long at Sea,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Shippe foule and vnwaſht, makes but ſmall way,</l>
                  <l>Doth neretheleſſe if that he ſpies a chace,</l>
                  <l>Vnto his courſes ſtraight his drablers lace,</l>
                  <l>And vp a trip hoyſe topſailes, though in vaine,</l>
                  <l>For foule, the more they ſayle, the leſſe they gaine:</l>
                  <l>So was it twixt faire <hi>ISIS</hi> and her foe;</l>
                  <l>For ſhe more lighter, did him faire outgoe.</l>
                  <l>Which when he ſaw, vexed to be ſo croſt,</l>
                  <l>Even like a <hi>Tyger</hi> fell, the which hath loſt</l>
                  <l>Vnwares her ſucking Whelpes, doth rage and fling,</l>
                  <l>Amid the ſhrubbes and buſhes that do ſpring,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:19"/>
                  <l> On <hi>Ganges</hi> golden ſtrond ſo tooke he on,</l>
                  <l>Stamping and ſtareing like a franticke man.</l>
                  <l>After ſtaying his rage, and lookeing round about:</l>
                  <l>In broken ſpeaches thus he did breake out.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now Heauens, I ſee my Godhead is but ſmall:</l>
                  <l>My power far leſſe, my might iuſt nought at all:</l>
                  <l>But ſhall I leaue her tho? No, I will after:</l>
                  <l>And neuer lin, till theſe ſame hands haue caught her:</l>
                  <l>Yet ſhe is young and wight, I o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e and ſlowe:</l>
                  <l>And as I followe, ſhe doth me outgoe.</l>
                  <l>Oh <hi>Cupid,</hi> why art thou mine enemie,</l>
                  <l>And to my griefe doſt giue no remedie?</l>
                  <l>Why ad'ſt thou ſtarres to heauen? leaues to green trees?</l>
                  <l>Why gathered waters, vnto growen Seas?</l>
                  <l>Why doſt thou make me languiſh for that Lady,</l>
                  <l>That is more coy, then euer I knew anie?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet you mine eyes were cauſe firſt of this ſame,</l>
                  <l>For thorow you deſcended beauties flame:</l>
                  <l>That in mine entrailes burnes like Mongibell,</l>
                  <l>But were mine eyes in fault? no I wot well,</l>
                  <l>Had my weake minde ore-rulde my greedie eye,</l>
                  <l>Then from this torment had I now bin free.</l>
                  <l>Here did he ſtop againe, and as you ſee,</l>
                  <l>Some well skilde actor in a tragedie,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe purpoſe bent to execute his will,</l>
                  <l>Is countermaunded by ſome vnlookt ill,</l>
                  <l>Falles like a madde man in a raging vaine:</l>
                  <l>Euen ſo did he, and thus began againe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My Harueſt is in Graſſe, I now do ſee,</l>
                  <l>And feare that it ripe Corne will neuer bee:</l>
                  <l>What tho; I am the ſelfe ſame God that hath</l>
                  <l>The Scepter of the Seas, who in my wrath</l>
                  <l>Can cauſe my raging Billowes to ariſe:</l>
                  <l>And armde with furie, buckle with the skies;</l>
                  <l>Then ſhal't be ſayd, that I ſhall ſuffer this,</l>
                  <l>And thus be croſt by ſcornefull <hi>Thamiſis?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:20"/>
                  <l> No? Who will then acknowledge me a King?</l>
                  <l>Or on my Aulters offer any thing?</l>
                  <l>Tis onely force muſt purchaſe me, what Loue</l>
                  <l>And my long woeing, from her nere could moue;</l>
                  <l>And though it be not gotten by conſtraint;</l>
                  <l>But kinde and gentle meane (they ſay) muſt gaint.<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet ſince I long haue gently woed her,</l>
                  <l>And all in vaine; by reuerend <hi>Stix</hi> I ſweare,</l>
                  <l>Hence foorth I will no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ger woe, nor ſew,</l>
                  <l>But ha'er in ſpight of all that ſhe can do.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O which of all the ſacred <hi>Muſes</hi> now,</l>
                  <l>Shall I entreat to ſhew the baſe meanes how</l>
                  <l>Falſe <hi>Neptune</hi> ſought to gaine his wiſhed pleaſure:</l>
                  <l>But one's too few, helpe therefore all together;</l>
                  <l>For well I wot, you hearing her ſad chaunce,</l>
                  <l>Did leaue your Springs bout which you wont to daunce,</l>
                  <l>And went to waile with her ſad Maydens, which</l>
                  <l>Did nothing elſe but cry, nought elſe but ſcritch.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now wearie <hi>Phaebus</hi> had vnharniſed</l>
                  <l>His fierie ſteedes, and got him ſelfe to bed</l>
                  <l>To his faire Loue: and now the ſable Night</l>
                  <l>Had cauſd ſleepe ceaze vpon each mortall wight.</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Neptune</hi> cauſd his Coatch be brought to him,</l>
                  <l>The which two yoaked <hi>Delphins</hi> makes to skim</l>
                  <l>Ore the large furrowes of his ſpacious plaines,</l>
                  <l>In which he mounted, and with ſcalie raignes,</l>
                  <l>Gouernd their heades; ſeated in Iuorie,</l>
                  <l>Like a great Prince adornd with maieſtie,</l>
                  <l>Bearing his three tinde Trident in his hand:</l>
                  <l>Whom <hi>Glaucus</hi> being accomp'ned with a band</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Tritons,</hi> followes till vnto the ground</l>
                  <l>They came, where windes in Irons faſt they found:</l>
                  <l>A cloudie Countrey, compaſt all with Hilles:</l>
                  <l>Where wreſtling windes with bluſtrous blaſting filles:</l>
                  <l>From darkſome Caues ſent out the foggie aire:</l>
                  <l>There <hi>Aeolus</hi> within a ſtately Chaire</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l> He found, holding his royall Mace in hand,</l>
                  <l>With which th'vnruly Windes he doth commaund,</l>
                  <l>Whom <hi>Neptune</hi> in this manner did intreate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>King <hi>Aeolus,</hi> for thee my brother ſet</l>
                  <l>To rule the Windes according to thy pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>To let them looſe, or keepe them lockt together.</l>
                  <l>On fartheſt ſhores of <hi>Ocean</hi> Seas there lyes</l>
                  <l>A pleaſant Iland, in triangle wiſe,</l>
                  <l>Which on the Eaſt the mouth of <hi>Rhyne</hi> doth face,</l>
                  <l>With a great Angle, and from thence apace</l>
                  <l>Withdrawes his ſhoring ſides, butting proudlie</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fraunce</hi> with the one, with th'other <hi>Germanie:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which Iland, doth in honour farre ſurpaſſe</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Creat;</hi> which my brother <hi>Joues</hi> nurſe whylome was.</l>
                  <l>Nor may with it <del>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </del> 
                     <hi>Samos</hi> or <hi>Rhodes</hi> compare:</l>
                  <l>Ore which, once <hi>Iuno,</hi> 
                     <del>or</del> 
                     <add>and</add> Loues Queene had care:</l>
                  <l>For there within that land, no lyuing wight</l>
                  <l>Hath want of needfull thing, or ſweete delight:</l>
                  <l>Nor are they ſcarde with blaſtes of bloody feares,</l>
                  <l>Which braying Trumpet ſoundes in fearefull eares;</l>
                  <l>But of the murthring and life quelling blade,</l>
                  <l>For Husbandmen there hookt Sithes oft are made,</l>
                  <l>And Huswiues there do hiue the little Bee,</l>
                  <l>In ruſty Caskes that by the walles do lie.</l>
                  <l>In this, there is a cruell, but faire Mayde,</l>
                  <l>Within whole haire, deceitfull Loue once made,</l>
                  <l>Slie ſubtile Nettes, by which all cloſely wrought,</l>
                  <l>My faynting ſenſes troytrouſly he caught,</l>
                  <l>When leaſt ſuſpecting; rauiſht at her ſight,</l>
                  <l>They on her rareneſſe fed with great delight:</l>
                  <l>And now ſixe Moones with borrowed brothers light,</l>
                  <l>Sixe times haue ſhynd, and ſixe times out of ſight</l>
                  <l>Bin, ſince I her gan woe; but all in vaine,</l>
                  <l>For from my ſuite is ſprung nought but diſdaine:</l>
                  <l>Foule ſcornes, that mocke me and my deitie,</l>
                  <l>And frowning lookes, all voyde of pietie.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:21"/>
                  <l> That Dame whoſe loſſe of life and chaſtetie,</l>
                  <l>Freede <hi>Rome</hi> from ſeruile yoake of tyrannie.</l>
                  <l>And that faire <hi>Isbell</hi> who would looſe her head,</l>
                  <l>Rather then yeeld to <hi>Pagans</hi> luſtfull bed,</l>
                  <l>Were not ſo coy, as is <hi>Doris</hi> proud daughter;</l>
                  <l>Witnes thoſe meanes, whereby ſo oft I ſought her:</l>
                  <l>Therefore th'vntamed windes, at my requeſt,</l>
                  <l>Send out againſt her, that by them oppreſt,</l>
                  <l>She may without conditions yeelde to mee,</l>
                  <l>And I thereby recure my maladie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now Ile enlarge thy ſtraighted Kingdomes bounds,</l>
                  <l>And giue to thee thy bordering neighbours grounds;</l>
                  <l>If yeelding, thou aſſentes to mee in this,</l>
                  <l>And helpe me get my wiſhed <hi>Thamiſis.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>This he with faigned ſighes ſo vttered,</l>
                  <l>That fooliſh <hi>Aeolus</hi> thought all he ſed</l>
                  <l>To be as true, and therefore pittying</l>
                  <l>The languiſhing eſtate of the olde King;</l>
                  <l>Without aduiſement, ſtraight made his replie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thrice Noble <hi>Neptune,</hi> whoſe dominions lie</l>
                  <l>Beyonde the borders of the ruddie <hi>Inde:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If I, or all my power, can bring to ende,</l>
                  <l>What you deſire, in vs ſhall want no will:</l>
                  <l>And therewith did he ſtrike thorow an hill</l>
                  <l>His Mace; whence ſtraight a crew of helliſh mates</l>
                  <l>In crowdes came thronging foorth the Iron gates;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe chiefe was <hi>Boreas,</hi> who with violent ſway,</l>
                  <l>Doth chaſe the peſtred Cloudes, and toſſe the Sea:</l>
                  <l>Who in his rage doth turne vp knottie Oakes,</l>
                  <l>And beates the ground in hayle with ſturdie ſtroakes;</l>
                  <l>Who trembling Ghoſtes doth vexe in <hi>Stigian</hi> lake;</l>
                  <l>And got in Caues, makes all the worlde to quake:</l>
                  <l>To whom turning, thus flattering <hi>Neptune</hi> ſayd,</l>
                  <l>You in your furie, make the worlde afrayd:</l>
                  <l>Turmoyling earth and ſeas, I did not locke</l>
                  <l>You, fettred with theſe ſtrong giues in this Rocke;</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:21"/>
                  <l> But frowning <hi>Joue,</hi> whoſe will for law muſt ſtand.</l>
                  <l>Nor with like tirranny do I commaunde,</l>
                  <l>You know: for in my Realme you may be bould,</l>
                  <l>Not any one gainſaying what you would.</l>
                  <l>Therfore ſtout <hi>Boreas,</hi> if <hi>Orithia</hi> thou</l>
                  <l>Didſt ere entirely loue, asſiſt we now,</l>
                  <l>T'obtaine my loue: who farre vnlike to thine,</l>
                  <l>Both ſcornes my perſon, and what els is mine.</l>
                  <l>Scarce this was ſaid, when ſturdy <hi>Boreas</hi> gan</l>
                  <l>To flaske his winges: with wauing which euen than</l>
                  <l>He raiſde a ſtorme, and with his companie,</l>
                  <l>Madde, and enragde, with furie thence did flie:</l>
                  <l>And like fierce Dogges, long time in Irons chainde,</l>
                  <l>And long in darkeſome kennelles haue remainde:</l>
                  <l>Once broken looſe, runne rageing heere and there,</l>
                  <l>And all they meete, with rauening teeth do teare.</l>
                  <l>So theſe ſame villaines now at libertie,</l>
                  <l>And freed from fetters, do a madding flie.</l>
                  <l>Troubling each place with their impetuous ſway,</l>
                  <l>And made the worlde ſeeme like a diſmall day:</l>
                  <l>Vntill they came where louely <hi>Thames</hi> abode,</l>
                  <l>Whom they did chaſe; baſe villaines, rude, and wood:</l>
                  <l>Not waighing ought the wrong ſhe offred had,</l>
                  <l>Nor yet the plaintes which her ſad maydens made.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But like how oft in ſtormie raynie weather,</l>
                  <l>The waters falling twentie howers together,</l>
                  <l>The flouds made proud thereby aboue their boundes,</l>
                  <l>Do ſwell and ouerflow the meddow groundes.</l>
                  <l>With the great furie of their ouerflowing,</l>
                  <l>Driuing ſmall Birds away from trees by growing:</l>
                  <l>Small Birds which on the ſpray had built their neſtes,</l>
                  <l>And cauſing fiſhes, as vnwonted gueſtes</l>
                  <l>To harbour in their roome: ſo <hi>ISIS</hi> was</l>
                  <l>Forc'd by the woodneſſe of fell <hi>Boreas:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To leaue her maydens pleaſaunt companies,</l>
                  <l>Who fild the aire with hoarſe vnwonted cryes</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:22"/>
                  <l> For her departure being ill opayd,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Niobe, Amphions</hi> Queene is ſayd,</l>
                  <l>When all her brood, the darlings of her ioy,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Latonas</hi> children did for ſpight deſtroy.</l>
                  <l>The hollow ſandie bankes that wont rebound,</l>
                  <l>To their rare charming muſicke; a ſweete ground,</l>
                  <l>Sent now vnpleaſant Ecchoes, like the notes</l>
                  <l>Came through the hollow of their feeble throates.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The light foote <hi>Fairies,</hi> and th'<hi>Oreades,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>Dryads, Hamadriads,</hi> and the <hi>Naiades,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who oft delighted with their harmonie,</l>
                  <l>Did by their ſtreames keepe <hi>ISIS</hi> companie:</l>
                  <l>Now hearing all theſes <hi>Nimphes</hi> ſo heauely mourne,</l>
                  <l>Like heauely at once vnto them goane,</l>
                  <l>Nere <hi>Thetis</hi> ſo bewailde ſtout <hi>Peleus</hi> ſonne,</l>
                  <l>When Coward <hi>Paris</hi> him to death had done.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Neuer <hi>Halcion</hi> with like griefe did mourne,</l>
                  <l>On ſandie ſea ſhore her deare ſpouſe forlorne:</l>
                  <l>Nor was the ſorrow my <hi>Phebe</hi> did make,</l>
                  <l>When death her dere-ling foorth her lap did take,</l>
                  <l>Though downe her cheekes did iſſue brackiſh ſeas,</l>
                  <l>To be compard vnto the ſorrow, theſe</l>
                  <l>Sad dolefull <hi>Nimphes</hi> did make, when they did ſee</l>
                  <l>The faire haird <hi>Thames</hi> in ſuch extremitie:</l>
                  <l>For like a Meade, diſpoyled of his flowers;</l>
                  <l>A goodly Picture, robbed of her colours:</l>
                  <l>Like to the Heauen, if all his Starres were loſt;</l>
                  <l>A goodly Shippe, wanting her Sayles and Maſt:</l>
                  <l>So faire eyed <hi>ISIS</hi> wanting, ſeemde that place;</l>
                  <l>Who thereof was the flower, the beautie, and grace:</l>
                  <l>And when as wordes free paſſage had obtayned,</l>
                  <l>Of presſing griefes, their harmes they thus complayned.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O who (quoth they) will make whole Seas fall downe</l>
                  <l>Our blubbred cheekes, where we our ſelues may drowne?</l>
                  <l>Or what God, full of pittie ſhall we call,</l>
                  <l>Who t'end our woes, to Rockes will turne vs all?</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:22"/>
                  <l> From hence foorth, Pleaſure be thou baniſhed</l>
                  <l>Out of this wretched place, and in thy ſtead</l>
                  <l>Let ouglie ſorrow dayly on vs tende.</l>
                  <l>And thou bright Sunne, would thou from hence wouldſt wend,</l>
                  <l>And let thy light in myſtie cloudes be pent,</l>
                  <l>For darkneſſe beſt beſitteth diſcontent:</l>
                  <l>And take her with thee, who borrowes her light</l>
                  <l>From the cleere rayes of thy moſt glorious ſight:</l>
                  <l>Take her, which oft amidd her <hi>Nimphes</hi> doth play</l>
                  <l>On <hi>Cinthus</hi> hill, and often times doth ſtay</l>
                  <l>Mongſt <hi>Stigian</hi> Hagges: for <hi>Thames</hi> deare to you both,</l>
                  <l>Is forſt to flie, for feare of <hi>Neptunes</hi> wroth.</l>
                  <l>And thou that wrapſt all in forgetfulneſſe,</l>
                  <l>And mortall folke doſt eaſe of heauineſſe,</l>
                  <l>Vnder thy blacke winges bringing diuers dreames</l>
                  <l>From foorth <hi>Cimerian</hi> fieldes, now hide the beames</l>
                  <l>Proroceeding from the Starres in th'Hemiſphere,</l>
                  <l>And make a generall darkneſſe euery where.</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Phylomell,</hi> ſince thou art woont to mone,</l>
                  <l>Remembring ſtill the great diſgrace was done</l>
                  <l>By thy falſe brother, helpe vs to lament:</l>
                  <l>Or if thy mourning notes are fully ſpent,</l>
                  <l>Then giue a quiet eare to that we ſay,</l>
                  <l>For we huge wronges in ſad tunes will diſplay.</l>
                  <l>And you ô Trees, in whom there life doth reſt,</l>
                  <l>Shew foorth ſome ſigne, as pittying our vnreſt.</l>
                  <l>Let little Birdes be ſilent on your ſpray:</l>
                  <l>And on your boughs, let Rauens croope by day.</l>
                  <l>But you that late your branches downe did bend,</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Thames</hi> faire face, the Sun-beames to defend,</l>
                  <l>Now in deſpight, to ground your branches throwe,</l>
                  <l>Since <hi>Thames</hi> is gone, to ſhew you waile her woe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>You Lillies white, whom whiter handes did gather:</l>
                  <l>And you faire blooming Roſes, Natures treaſure,</l>
                  <l>Vpon your ſelues ſadde ſable Weedes beſtow,</l>
                  <l>Since <hi>Thames</hi> is gone, to ſhew you wayle her woe.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:23"/>
                  <l> She was the Roſe, the Lillie of the day,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe leaues b'vntimely ſtormes, do fall away:</l>
                  <l>Oh eccho all this place, with mouring fill,</l>
                  <l>And marke the dolefull accents of our ill.</l>
                  <l>Sound foorth our griefe, and let them neuer end,</l>
                  <l>Vntill the Heauens our fortunes do amend.</l>
                  <l>Oh let our iuſt complayninges loude and ſhrill,</l>
                  <l>Thorow theſe winding waters wander ſtill,</l>
                  <l>Whereby thoſe ſeas that on our ſhores do flow,</l>
                  <l>Our heauie griefe to forraigne lands may ſhow:</l>
                  <l>And on their banckes let neuer trees more grow,</l>
                  <l>Since <hi>Thams</hi> is gone, as ſigne you waile her woe.</l>
                  <l>And thou great <hi>Joue,</hi> if any care thou haſt</l>
                  <l>Of earth, or earthly thinges, O do thou haſte,</l>
                  <l>And ſaue her from falſe <hi>Neptunes</hi> treacherie,</l>
                  <l>Who honoured ſtill thy ſacred deitie:</l>
                  <l>Saue who the corners of thine Aulters dud</l>
                  <l>Purple continually with luke warme bloud.</l>
                  <l>But ô! it ſeemes great <hi>Joue,</hi> thou haſt no care</l>
                  <l>Of vs, nor of this worlde; but it doth ere,</l>
                  <l>At all aduenture: for if that you had</l>
                  <l>Regard of humane thinges, or if you made</l>
                  <l>Eſteeme of vs, your owne hands workemanſhyp;</l>
                  <l>Then would you of ſad <hi>ISIS</hi> take ſome keepe,</l>
                  <l>And her protect from <hi>Neptune,</hi> who amine</l>
                  <l>Doth ſeeke her ſpotleſſe chaſtetie to ſtaine:</l>
                  <l>And he ſhould not, that hath ſo laboured</l>
                  <l>T'abuſe chaſt Maydens, ſcape vnpuniſhed:</l>
                  <l>Wherefore ſince Heauen, and all therein are deafe,</l>
                  <l>And hearing not, can not amende our griefe,</l>
                  <l>Let vs be gone, and ceaſe hence foorth to plaine,</l>
                  <l>For all our plaintes are ſpent, but all in vaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This ſaid, they all aroſe, all yll apayde,</l>
                  <l>And thence departed, in diſpaire of ayde</l>
                  <l>From heauen, or elie where; vexing ſtill the skies,</l>
                  <l>With their hot ſcalding ſighes and greeuous cries:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:23"/>
                  <l> But nor the cryes, nor ſighes, did <hi>ISIS</hi> good,</l>
                  <l>Whom <hi>Boreas</hi> foule vnciuill Groome ſtarke wood,</l>
                  <l>Did with a crew of wicked mates purſue,</l>
                  <l>As ſhe ſome Felon were, or wight vntrue:</l>
                  <l>Who poore ſoule, ſeeing how ſhe was oreborne,</l>
                  <l>Like pittious plaintes did make, and ſo did mourne,</l>
                  <l>As with her husband <hi>Epimethius</hi> daughter</l>
                  <l>Did then when they could ſee nothing but water;</l>
                  <l>When onely they of all mankind bereft,</l>
                  <l>Amid the billowes of the Seas were left.</l>
                  <l>Then when themſelues were ſolely left in woe,</l>
                  <l>And ſaw no land, nor any fellowes moe,</l>
                  <l>And fearing leaſt at laſt ſhe might be caught,</l>
                  <l>By that foule Leatcher, who this wrong firſt wrought:</l>
                  <l>With hands lift vp, ſhe thus beſought great <hi>Joue.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Heare thou great Father of the Gods aboue,</l>
                  <l>By whom all's made, maintained, and diſpoſde,</l>
                  <l>And from whom nought on earth is vndiſcloſde:</l>
                  <l>Who full of equitie, doſt all things right,</l>
                  <l>And wicked folke beholds with eies of ſpight.</l>
                  <l>Heare and behold the miſerable ſtate,</l>
                  <l>Of me thy Daughter, dolfull, deſolate.</l>
                  <l>Theſe teares, ay me, that from mine eies do fall,</l>
                  <l>For ſuccour at thy helping hands do call.</l>
                  <l>Oh let not then my foe obtaine his will,</l>
                  <l>On me poore Maide: nor let the windes fulfill</l>
                  <l>The treaſon that he hath deuiſd gainſt mee:</l>
                  <l>But force them all retire, and bacward flee,</l>
                  <l>To their abode; O pittie me I pray,</l>
                  <l>Leaſt following ages doe hereafter ſay,</l>
                  <l>In vaine thou holdes the thunder in thy hand,</l>
                  <l>Not helping thoſe that helpe of thee demaunde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So prayed <hi>Thamiſis,</hi> and ſtraight great <hi>Joue,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shaking his head, thrice thundred from aboue,</l>
                  <l>In ſigne he heard, and called <hi>Mercurie,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Charging him ſtraight vnto <hi>Aeolia</hi> hie,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:24"/>
                  <l> And tell the King when firſt I did accorde,</l>
                  <l>Ouer the wraſtling windes, to make him Lords</l>
                  <l>I gaue in chardg he no man ſhould opreſſe,</l>
                  <l>But ſeeke ſtill offerd iniuries to redreſſe.</l>
                  <l>But ſince with <hi>Neptune,</hi> he confederate is,</l>
                  <l>To wrong my tender darling <hi>Thameſis:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If he his windes do not in haſt reclaime,</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Sytx</hi> tell him, to his eternall ſhame,</l>
                  <l>Like how with <hi>Titans</hi> rude rebellious race,</l>
                  <l>I whilome dealt: ſo will I him diſgrace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet for this wrong, which is alreadie done,</l>
                  <l>At what time, twixt the place where ſets the Sunne,</l>
                  <l>And the right Northen Pole, there doth appeare,</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Caſsiopeia,</hi> ſeated in her Chaire:</l>
                  <l>Within that milkie way, made by my Queene,</l>
                  <l>A blaſing Commet, like fier flameing ſheene;</l>
                  <l>Which ſhall be ere <hi>Apollo</hi> eight times leads</l>
                  <l>Aboute the <hi>Zodiake</hi> his trampling ſteades:</l>
                  <l>Two princely Beaſtes ſhall come from <hi>Thames</hi> coole ſtreame</l>
                  <l>Which ſhall more dammadge do vndo his Realme,</l>
                  <l>Then did that mightie Boore <hi>Diana</hi> ſent,</l>
                  <l>The Fielde of <hi>Calidon</hi> to ſpill or rent:</l>
                  <l>All (quoth he) in reuenge he durſt attempt,</l>
                  <l>To wrong her, whom from wrong I haue exempt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This ſaide, faire <hi>Maias</hi> Sonne the ſubtil God,</l>
                  <l>Takeing in haſt his dead ſleepe charming rod,</l>
                  <l>And winged ſhooes, did leaue the chriſtall ſkie,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ioues</hi> princely Pallace, where continually</l>
                  <l>Th'erraticke ſtarres in their ſweete harmonie,</l>
                  <l>Do make rare ſoundes of heauenly melodie:</l>
                  <l>And downe from thence, vnto this lower worlde,</l>
                  <l>Swifter then thunder bolt, himſelfe he hurlde,</l>
                  <l>And ſought King <hi>Aeolus:</hi> to whom he ſtraight,</l>
                  <l>The purport of his coming, did dilate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Haue any ere in May a Garden ſeene,</l>
                  <l>With diuers ſlowers enameld freſh and greene,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:24"/>
                  <l> And it reuewes when <hi>Phoebus</hi> is declinde</l>
                  <l>Vnto the Southerne pole, the ſame doth finde</l>
                  <l>Oregrowne with wilde weedes, and with ſtinking graſſe;</l>
                  <l>Now would haue ſayd, in <hi>Aeolus</hi> there was</l>
                  <l>Like change, hearing great <hi>Ioues</hi> Embaſſadour:</l>
                  <l>For neuer was he troubled ſo before,</l>
                  <l>Saue when his Nephewes bawling did detect,</l>
                  <l>His Childrens lewd crime, and inceſtious fact:</l>
                  <l>For which, the guiltleſſe Babe as puniſhment,</l>
                  <l>He caſt to Dogs, which it in peecemeale rent;</l>
                  <l>And to deſilde <hi>Canace,</hi> ſent a ſworde;</l>
                  <l>With which her owne ſelfe to the heart ſhe gor'de:</l>
                  <l>For he much feared <hi>Joue</hi> his Soueraigne,</l>
                  <l>Knowing he might depoſe him from his Raigne</l>
                  <l>And regall power: therefore t'amend his fault,</l>
                  <l>And pleaſe the angrie God, Poſtillians ſtraight</l>
                  <l>He after <hi>Boreas</hi> ſent, and did commaunde</l>
                  <l>To bring them backe, and ceaſe their ſute in hand:</l>
                  <l>Who neuer ſtayed, till they the windes had founde,</l>
                  <l>And brought them backe, and them againe had bounde</l>
                  <l>In their baſe bondes of during Iron, wrought</l>
                  <l>Long ſince in <hi>Aetna</hi> by the <hi>Cyclops:</hi> taught</l>
                  <l>Their art by Lymping <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulcan,</hi> who was plaſt there</l>
                  <l>To be <hi>Joues</hi> workeman, and the cheife Forge-maiſter;</l>
                  <l>Wherby diſtreſſed <hi>Thameſis</hi> was freed,</l>
                  <l>From thoſe that had her ouerthrow decree'd</l>
                  <l>And backe return'd to her ſad <hi>Nimphs,</hi> whom ſhe</l>
                  <l>Did finde, her loſſe bewailing heauily:</l>
                  <l>Who when they ſaw her firſt, far'd like to her</l>
                  <l>Hath but one Sonne; that for a Souldier</l>
                  <l>Preſt, in his Princes ſeruice forth is gone,</l>
                  <l>To keepe his Countrie from inuaſion;</l>
                  <l>Whom fearing to be drowned in the deepe,</l>
                  <l>Or by hard ſteele ſent t'euerlaſting ſleepe,</l>
                  <l>Shee doth bewaile as dead, and will not be</l>
                  <l>When he returnes, from death and daunger free,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12019:25"/>
                  <l> Perſwaded tis her Sonne, but ſome vaine ſight,</l>
                  <l>That would with idle ſhadowes her delight,</l>
                  <l>Till her cold feares are paſt; for all of them</l>
                  <l>thinking her wholly loſt, thought they had ſeene</l>
                  <l>Her ſhadow, not her ſelfe, till ſhe ſpake to them:</l>
                  <l>What time aſſured, they all receiued her,</l>
                  <l>As an <hi>Hungarian</hi> Father doth his heire,</l>
                  <l>And only Sonne: which hath a longſome time,</l>
                  <l>Mongſt hated <hi>Turkes,</hi> in helliſh priſon line:</l>
                  <l>Their ſighes to ſongs, their teares now almoſt ſpent,</l>
                  <l>They turn'd to laughter, and to merriment;</l>
                  <l>And thankt the motor of the whirling Spheres,</l>
                  <l>That had not them forgot drowned in teares.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But ſtay my Muſe, the Skie is faire and cleare,</l>
                  <l>The Seas are calme, no winde doth whiſtle heere;</l>
                  <l>Heere let vs anchour then, for heere we may</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>afe, to morrow being Holiday.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
